<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christos autotheos, or, An historical account of the heresie denying the Godhead of Christ</title>
            <author>Addison, Lancelot, 1632-1703.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26363</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A516</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11751</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12331780</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12331780</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59696</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26363)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 908:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christos autotheos, or, An historical account of the heresie denying the Godhead of Christ</title>
                  <author>Addison, Lancelot, 1632-1703.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 107, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Hodgkin for Robert Clavell ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Part of title transliterated from Greek.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to Lancelot Addison. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[4] at end.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Divinity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59696:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59696:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΧΡΙΣΤΟΣ 'ΑΥΤΟ'ΘΕΟΣ OR AN Hiſtorical Account OF THE HERESIE Denying the GODHEAD OF CHRIST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Hodgkin</hi> for <hi>Robert Clavell,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Peacoak</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59696:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59696:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>AFter the Hereſie denying the Divinity of Chriſt had been long ſilenced by Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Diſcipline, it was again brought upon the Stage by <hi>Arius,</hi> whoſe Character makes not much for its Credit. For tho' in holy Orders, he was proud and aſpiring, ſubtle witted, and an excellent Proficient in the Art of Flattery. Beſides he was one that had ſuch an overweaning Conceit of his own Abilities, that he thought all to be his Inferiours in <hi>Deſert.</hi> And through this his vain unhappy Temper he became impatient of Contradiction, full of Envy and Stomach, and bold to broach Hereſie. And it was obſerved That Diſcipline and good Counſel, which uſually make others better, made <hi>Arius</hi> the worſe; and the more his Hereſie was condemned, the more he labour'd to propagate and defend it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sulpitius lib. 2.</hi> obſerves, that the <hi>Arian</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie receiv'd no ſmall Advantage from the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Perſons choſen to be its publick Managers. Who (as he tells us) were <hi>Senes callidi,</hi> old ſtanch
<pb facs="tcp:59696:3"/>Diſputants, who had been long vers'd in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie. Whereas the Managers choſen by the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox,</hi> were Young Men, <hi>parùm docti &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rùm cauti,</hi> fuller of <hi>Warmth</hi> than of <hi>Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
               <q>And this had a great Influence upon the Cauſe, all Men concluding of the reſt on either ſide, by the Quality of the Managers.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, the <hi>Orthodox</hi> dealt plainly, argued with Openneſs and Simplicity, and in their <hi>Forms</hi> of <hi>Confeſſion</hi> were clear and ingenuous. Whereas the Hereticks wrought with great Subtilty, decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning no Artifice that might advantage their Cauſe; and in their Confeſſions, they loved Ambiguity and Equivocation, and (which did not a little turn to their Advantage) they always laboured to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in the ſeveral Emperours &amp; their Favourites a good liking of their Doctrine, and either to gain them to it, or not greatly to diſapprove it.</p>
            <p>But (according to an Ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) it may juſtly create our Wonder,
<note place="margin">Phrob. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tna Ar.</note> that notwithſtanding the Authors of this Venom are long ſince dead and gone, the wicked Doctrine ſhou'd ſtill remain, and that after ſo many Confutations and Cenſures there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, any ſhou'd be found to maintain and dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it. But our Wonder will ceaſe when we conſider with judicious <hi>Hooker</hi>
               <q>That the Weeds of Hereſie being grown up to Ripeneſs, do even in cutting down ſometimes ſcatter thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:59696:3"/>Seeds, which for a while lie unſeen and buried in the Earth, but afterwards freſhly ſpring up again no leſs pernicious than at the firſt.</q> And the ſame learned Author obſerves, that the Hereſies concerning the Holy Trinity have of later Years grown up no where ſo faſt as where the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed and the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria Patri</hi> have not been made uſe of. And no Wonder that Hereſies ſhould thrive in thoſe Places where the beſt Preſervatives againſt them have been neglected.</p>
            <p>For as to the <hi>Creed</hi> of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> what is it elſe, but a Divine Explication of the chief Articles of the Chriſtian Faith? Which <hi>Creed</hi> was ſo highly valued by the Church, that ſhe made it part of her Liturgy. And as for the <hi>Gloria,</hi> or the <hi>Hymns</hi> and <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> they were a Part of the Liturgy long before the <hi>Athanaſian Belief:</hi> And they were ever look'd upon as an heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Acclamation of joyful Applauſe to his Praiſe in whom we believe. And from the beginning the Church of Chriſt by a ſecret univerſal Impulſe of God's Spirit, always ty'd it ſelf to end neither Sermon nor almoſt any ſpecial Matter wherein the Things of God were concerned, without ſome peculiar Words of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Glory to the Trinity, which all true Chriſtians believe and worſhip. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb facs="tcp:59696:4"/>omitted to do this, was ſuſpected to want a right Faith of the Trinity, and to doubt of the Equality of the Perſons: For if we really believe,
<q>The Godhead of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt, to be all one, the Glory Equal, and the Majeſty Coeternal,</q> why do we not publickly own it, by aſcribing equal Glory to each of them? And where can we do this with more Solemnity than at the Cloſe of thoſe <hi>Homilies</hi> and <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> which we make unto the People? The Uſe of the <hi>Gloria</hi> was never quarrell'd at or omitted by any till <hi>Arius,</hi> who being preſs'd with this Uſage of the Church, as an Argument againſt the Hereſie which makes the <hi>Son</hi> inferiour to the <hi>Father,</hi> labour'd to corrupt this Hymn, ſaying, <hi>Glory be to the Father, by the Son, in the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> But the Church was careful to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ancient Uſage,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Con. Va. c.</hi> 7.</note> adding on Purpoſe againſt <hi>Arius, As it was in the Beginning, is now, and ever ſhall be.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Gloria Patri</hi> it has ever been eſteem'd the Chriſtians <hi>Creed</hi> and <hi>Hymn.</hi> For the Summ of the Chriſtians Faith is the Myſtery of the <hi>Trinity,</hi> by which he declares againſt all <hi>Hereticks</hi> in the World. And it is alſo the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians Hymn wherewith he ought to cloſe all his Religious Services, Praiſes, Prayers, Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings,
<pb facs="tcp:59696:4"/>Confeſſion of Faith and Sins. And as to the great Myſtery contain'd in the <hi>Gloria,</hi> it was well with Chriſtianity when Men went no farther therein than the Scripture led them, and when they reſted in ſuch Diſcoveries of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity as God has been pleas'd to give in his Word. By which Word if we wou'd once guide our Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and ſubmit them to it, we might hope to ſee all thoſe Diſputes buried in ſilence, which now make ſo great a Noiſe: <hi>Ridente Turcâ, non dolente Judaeo.</hi> And if thoſe very Men, who are at preſent ſo keenly engag'd in Debates about the Trinity, wou'd ſpeak out, they wou'd tell us <hi>That Trinity in Unity, and Unity in Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> is a Myſtery ſurpaſſing their Abilities to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain, and that it ſurmounts the Power of humane Nature to give a ſatisfactory Anſwer to all the Doubts, Cavils and Queſtions which bold Men may raiſe about it.</p>
            <p>Let the Myſteries of Chriſtianity continue at that Diſtance where God has ſet them to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd and ador'd, and then Peace and Truth will meet and embrace.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:59696:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59696:5"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR AN Hiſtorical Account OF THE HERESIE Denying the GODHEAD of CHRIST.</head>
            <p>WE may know the better how to determine of the Opinion which denies the Divinity of our Saviour, if we purſue it through its whole Hiſtory, and conſider where it firſt took Root, when it began to ſpread, and how in time it over-ran ſo great a Part of the Chriſtian Church. Now in doing this, we muſt look beyond the Annals of Chriſtianity: For long before that Chriſtianity was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59696:6"/>known by Name in the World, its Author was robb'd of his Godhead, by that very People which hop'd for the largeſt Benefits from him. For at leaſt, ever ſince the Schools of the <hi>Rabbins</hi> gain'd Authority a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Jews,</hi> that infatuated Nation have been of Opinion, that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> whom they ſtill expect, is not to be the Son of God in that Senſe in which the Chriſtians own him to be the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Holy Trinity: For tho' the <hi>Jews</hi> by many Texts of Scripture, prove that the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhall be the Son of God, yet they hold he is not to be the Son of God by Nature, but only by Deputation: So that they deny his Eternal Exiſtence and Deity. Now this is an Opinion which was afterwards followed by thoſe <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> who held the Kingdom of Chriſt was not perpetual and eternal; and that he was made the Son of God only from the time that he took our Fleſh, and was born of the Virgin. When Chriſt put that Queſtion to his Diſciples, <hi>Whom do Men ſay, that I, the Son of Man am?</hi> He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon a double Error in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men the <hi>Jews,</hi> concerning the <hi>Meſſiah.</hi> The firſt Error reſpected the Manner of his coming among them, which they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected ſhou'd be in Secular Pomp and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59696:6"/>Grandeur, and attended with the Conqueſt and ſubduing of the Nations. From which Error he labour'd to withdraw their Minds, by recalling them to the original Promiſe of his Coming, and ſhewing them that the end thereof was not to conquer Kingdoms, but to bruiſe the Serpent's Head; and to manifeſt that he was the Seed of the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, which was promiſed to do this, he takes upon him no higher Title than that of the SON of MAN. A ſecond Error the <hi>Jews</hi> had imbib'd concerning the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> reſpected his Deſcent: For they were uncertain whether he was to ariſe from the Living or from the Dead; which Doubt Chriſt alſo fully cleared, when he expreſly owned himſelf to be the Son of Man, or the Son that was promiſed to the firſt Man, who ſhould be born from the Seed of the Woman. Chriſt did not ſo much enquire whether the <hi>Jews</hi> thought him to be the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> as what kind of Perſon they thought him to be, as he was the <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias:</hi> So that the Queſtion he put to his Diſciples did not ſo much regard his Perſon, as the Quality of his Perſon, and whether the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> whom they all acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd, ſhou'd be the Son of Man, was not alſo to be the Son of God, not only by Adoption, Deputation and Promotion;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59696:7"/>but by Nature. And the Diſciples return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Anſwer to their Maſter's Queſtion, according to the Opinion the Multitude had of him, telling him that ſome took him for <hi>John the Baptiſt,</hi> ſome for <hi>Elias,</hi> and ſome for one of the old Prophets, who was either returned to Life, or elſe that the Soul of one of them was tranſmigrated and come into his Body; which Opinion the <hi>Phariſees</hi> had borrowed of the <hi>Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goreans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when the Diſciples had given Chriſt this Account of the various Sentiments the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> People had of the Quality of his Perſon, he was pleas'd to ask them their Opinion of him; <hi>But whom do ye (my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples) ſay that I am?</hi> To which Demand, <hi>Simon Peter</hi> in the Name of the reſt, makes this Reply: <hi>Thou art the Chriſt, the Son of the living God.</hi> The Anſwer is not only wonderfully emphatical by reaſon of the Multitude of Articles that are in it; but alſo becauſe that <hi>Peter</hi> did not return it of his own Head, nor by any Dictate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to that of the Holy Ghoſt:
<q>For Fleſh and Blood (as they ſignifie meer Man in Oppoſition to God) did not put this Anſwer in <hi>Simon</hi>'s Mouth, but it was immediately from Heaven:</q> For from thence he was inſpired to declare, that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59696:7"/>Jeſus was the true <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and by Nature the Son of the living God. He needed no Revelation to enable him to confeſs that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> was the Son of God by Deputation: Every ordinary <hi>Jew</hi> could have told him ſo much: For it was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally believed that when ever God ſhould be pleaſed to ſend the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> he would depute him to be his Son; but that he was to be his Son by Nature: Very God of very God, was no Article in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Creed. And this great Truth was not founded on Humane Teſtimony, nor on the Votes and Wiſhes of Men, but on the Teſtimony of God himſelf: For it was he that put it into <hi>Peter</hi>'s Mind to declare the Divinity of Chriſt, and by that Means to ſettle the uncertain wavering Thoughts that were on Foot, concerning the Quality of the Perſon of the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> and that it might be no longer doubted that he was God. The Divinity of Chriſt is indeed the Rock on which the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church is built, and that which makes it ſtand impregnable againſt the Gates of Hell, the greateſt Power and Artifice that can poſſibly be uſed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy it.</p>
            <p>From what has now been intimated, we may conclude, that the Denial of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59696:8"/>Chriſt's Divinity, came originally from the <hi>Jews,</hi> and that it is an Opinion which receiv'd its full Confutation from Heaven: So that it may juſtly create our Wonder, that after ſo ſolemn a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion as <hi>Peter</hi> Made of Chriſt's Divinity, and that too by the Dictate of God himſelf, that any who believe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſhou'd be ſo hardly as to gainſay it. But ſeeing it has happened to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, and that among the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity ſome have ſo far Judaiz'd in this Particular, as ſacrilegiouſly to rob our Lord of his Divinity. We are next to conſider who and what ſort of Perſons they were that firſt did thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius,</hi> upon whoſe Authority I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend in this Point, writes, how that one <hi>Theodotus</hi> was the Inventer of this Atheiſtical Opinion, and that he was a Man of mean Education, being by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion a Tanner. This Man drew into his Hereſie another of his own Name, who was a Banker, and both together proſelyted <hi>Aſclepiodotus;</hi> of whoſe Quality and Condition the Hiſtorian makes no mention. This <hi>Aſclepiodotus</hi> gained to his Opinion <hi>Natalis,</hi> a Confeſſour, a Man of Piety and good Meaning; who being afterwards convinced of his Error, recant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59696:8"/>it. This Hereſie was no ſooner heard of, but it was exploded and writ againſt, and Enquiry made after thoſe who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained it. And one <hi>Artemon</hi> being found a zealous Stickler in Defence of this blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous Hereſie, it was called the Hereſie of <hi>Artemon:</hi> In Confutation of which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Pieces were compoſed by the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, evincing that the Opinion which aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted our Saviour to be meer Man, was an Innovation of late Date amongſt the Chriſtians. Of thoſe Tracts that were written on this Argument, none was ſo elaborate as that called the <hi>Little Labyrinth;</hi> whoſe Author, according to <hi>Nicephorus,</hi> is unknown: And <hi>Theodoret</hi> who mentions the Story of <hi>Theodotus</hi> the Tanner, and <hi>Natalis</hi> the Biſhop, atteſts that he had taken it out of the Book called the <hi>Little Labyrinth. Photinus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, that <hi>Caius</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Presbyter, living in the Time of the Pope's, <hi>Victor</hi> and <hi>Zephyrin,</hi> in the Year 199, wrote a Book againſt the Hereſie of <hi>Artemon,</hi> but ſays that it was not the ſame with the <hi>Little Labyrinth.</hi> But to proceed out of the <hi>Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Labyrinth, Euſebius</hi> tells us, that thoſe who affirmed our Saviour to be a meer Man, boaſted much of the Antiquity of their Opinion, and how that all the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59696:9"/>and the very Apoſtles themſelves received and taught the ſame things that they aſſerted; and that the ſame was taught till the Times of <hi>Victor,</hi> who from <hi>Peter</hi> was the thirteenth Biſhop of <hi>Rome;</hi> but that when <hi>Zephyrinus</hi> was made Pope, the ſame Opinion began to be adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, which (ſaith <hi>Euſebius</hi> out of the <hi>Little Labyrinth</hi>) might ſeem probable, if it were not contradicted by the ſacred Scriptures, and the Writings of ſome Chriſtians ancienter than the Times of <hi>Victor,</hi> who lived in the End of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond <hi>Century:</hi> For <hi>Juſtin,</hi> who died a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Year 166, and <hi>Tatianus</hi> who lived about the ſame time; as alſo <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens,</hi> wrote in the Defence of the Truth, againſt the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and the Hereſies of their own Times; and theſe in all their Books have maintained the Divinity of Chriſt. And who is he that is ignorant of the Books of <hi>Irenaeus, Melito</hi> the <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Biſhop, and others, which declare Chriſt to be God and Man? <hi>Pliny</hi> (in his Epiſtle to <hi>Trajan</hi>) tells him how it was the Cuſtom of the Chriſtians to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe Pſalms and Hymns in Honour of Chriſt, in which they attributed Divinity to him, and ſang forth his Praiſes as God. Theſe very Pſalms and Hymns,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59696:9"/>written at the Beginning of Chriſtianity by its faithful Profeſſors, yield an unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Atteſtation of their believing Chriſt to be God. So that the Hereticks who firſt held the contrary, had no reaſon to ſay that their Opinion was the Creed of the Primitive Chriſtians: And it is a ſhameleſs Falſity to affirm, that <hi>Victor,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> was of their Judgment: For <hi>Victor</hi> was ſo far from abetting thoſe who held Chriſt to be a meer Man, that he condignly puniſhed them; as was evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in the Caſe of <hi>Theodotus</hi> the Tanner (the Founder of this Apoſtacy) whom <hi>Victor</hi> excommunicated and proſcrib'd: Which certainly he would not have done, had he been of the ſame Judgment with him. Thus ſtood Affairs in the Times of <hi>Victor,</hi> and in what Poſture they were in the Days of his Succeſſor <hi>Zephyrinus,</hi> who was made Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> about the ninth Year of <hi>Severus</hi>'s Empire, comes now to be recounted.</p>
            <p>The Perſon that compil'd the Book concerning the execrable Hereſie, now treated of, relates a very remarkable Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage that happened in the Days of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyrinus,</hi> concerning one <hi>Natalis,</hi> who, as <hi>Valeſius</hi> conjectures, was that <hi>Caecilius Natalis,</hi> who, by a Diſpute of <hi>Octavius Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuarius</hi>'s
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59696:10"/>before <hi>Minucius Felix</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> was converted to the Chriſtian Faith; as <hi>Minucius Felix</hi> relates in his Dialogue; and the Name, the Time, and the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this Perſon, do all agree to make this probable.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Natalis</hi> was a Confeſſor, and liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the Time when the <hi>Little Labyrinth</hi> was compoſed; but by the Craft of <hi>Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clepiodotus</hi> and <hi>Theodotus</hi> the Banker, both Diſciples of <hi>Theodotus</hi> the Tanner, he was ſeduced to their Opinion, and perſuaded by them to be elected a Biſhop of their Hereſie. And the moſt prevailing Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>Natalis</hi> to accept of this Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, was the Conſideration of a monthly Salary, amounting to an hundred and fifty Pence, which they promiſed duly to pay him. <hi>Natalis</hi> being thus made a Biſhop, turned a vehement Aſſertor of the Hereſie of <hi>Theodotus;</hi> but he did not long therein continue with any Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dateneſs or Complacency: For by <hi>Viſions</hi> in his Sleep, he was frequently admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by our Lord, whoſe Compaſſion towards him was ſo great, that he would not let him who had been a Witneſs of his own Sufferings, to periſh in his Hereſie, and under Excommunication. But <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis</hi> being bewitch'd with the Bait of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59696:10"/>Primacy among thoſe of his Sect, and with the Lucre he got by being their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, he regarded not the Viſions he had in his Sleep, but continu'd as zealous in the Defence of his Opinion, as if he had never been warned from Heaven to reject it. Whereupon it pleaſed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate God to ſend his holy Angels to chaſtize him, who for a whole Night having loaded him with ſevere Stripes, he was therewith ſo far awaken'd, that he thought of nothing but a ſpeedy Recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Repentance: And riſing very early the next Morning, he put on Sack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, and beſprinkled himſelf with Aſhes, and with Tears in his Eyes, proſtrated himſelf before <hi>Zephyrinus</hi> the Biſhop, and fell down not only at the Feet of the Clergy, but of the Laity alſo; and with Tears mov'd the Compaſſion of the Church; which having view'd the print of the Stripes he had received, and obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his ſorrowful Carriage, and other Tokens of his Repentance, at laſt, tho' with great Difficulty, ſhe admitted him into her Communion.</p>
            <p>But beſides the <hi>Little Labyrinth,</hi> out of which <hi>Euſebius</hi> tranſcribed this Story of <hi>Natalis,</hi> he takes notice of other Books written againſt the Hereticks, that denied
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59696:11"/>Chriſt to be God, which Books repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them to have been Perſons of the vileſt Impiouſneſs and Immorality: And ſuch as impudently adulterated the ſacred Scriptures, rejected the Canon of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive <hi>Faith,</hi> and were ignorant of Chriſt: For they neglected the holy Bible; and inſtead of enquiring into its Meaning, they laboured to obſcure the Light there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, beſtowing their Pains in finding out ſuch Schemes of Argumentation as might confirm the Syſtem of their Impiety. If any propos'd unto them a Text of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Scriptures, they examined whether a connex or a disjunctive Propoſition, might be made out of it; and inſtead of ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Word of God, they applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to Geometry, and to the reading of <hi>Euclid, Ariſtotle, Theophraſtus</hi> and <hi>Galen;</hi> admiring the Books the laſt had written concerning the Forms of Syllogiſms, and the whole Body of Philoſophy. They made uſe alſo of the Arts of Infidels for the Confirmation of their Heretical Opinion; and by the Craft of ſome Atheiſts, they adulterated the ſincere Authority of the divine Scriptures, on which they impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently laid their Hands, ſaying, that it ought to be corrected: They put out ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Copies of the Bible; which Copies,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59696:11"/>upon Examination, and comparing them one with another, were found to be very diſagreeing: For the Copies of <hi>Aſclepiodotus</hi> were much different from thoſe of <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus;</hi> and the Diſciples of each of them la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured diligently to amend the Correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their Maſters. The Copies of <hi>Hermophilus</hi> differed from thoſe of <hi>Aſclepio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus;</hi> and thoſe Copies of Scripture, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Apollonides</hi> differed one from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: But all the Copies agree in an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious wreſting and deforming the Word of God: And we may well imagine that theſe Hereticks were not ignorant of their wicked Acting in depraving the divine Scriptures: For either they did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the divine Scriptures to have been dictated by the Holy Spirit, and then they were Infidels: Or if they did believe this, and yet went about to correct them, then they muſt think themſelves wiſer than the Holy Ghoſt, and what were they then but mad Men? For they cannot deny this their bold Fact in correcting the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures to have been done by them; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Copies were written by their own Hands: And they did never pretend to have received ſuch Copies as they produc'd, from thoſe who were their Inſtructers; nor could they ever ſhew the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59696:12"/>Copies out of which they tranſcrib'd their pretended Corrections. But this was not all, for the old Hereticks, who denied Chriſt to be God, were not content only to corrupt the Scriptures, to make them ſpeak in Favour of their Hereſie; but ſome of them quite rejected both the Law and the Prophets, under a Pretence of the Grace given by the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>This is the Account which <hi>Euſebius</hi> gives of the firſt Impugners of the Divinity of our Lord: And they appear to have been bold, crafty, aſſuming Men: Men of that Impudence, as to affirm the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, even the Apoſtles themſelves, to have been of their Opinion; tho' they can't be ignorant, how that both the Inſpired Scriptures, and the firſt and beſt Chriſtian Writers atteſted the quite contrary: And had we no other Proof hereof than the Pſalms and Hymns compoſed and ſung by the firſt Chriſtians in Praiſe of Chriſt, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven theſe wou'd ſufficiently demonſtrate that they did own him to be true God, or elſe we muſt conclude them to have been Idolaters, who ſang thoſe Hymns to him as God. But the Villany and Poiſon of theſe Hereticks was moſt ſignally diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play'd in thoſe Corruptions of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, which they called Corrections:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59696:12"/>For this was to envenome the Spring, and to keep both themſelves and others from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver coming to the Knowledge of the Truth. But their Devices and Councils were all diſappointed in their Diſagreement about that which they called the Corrections of Scripture: For they cou'd never hit of any Harmony in their Copies, nor determine which of their correct Copies of Scripture, ſhou'd be the Conon.</p>
            <p>After the Hereſie of <hi>Artemon</hi> had been condemned and refuted by the Writers of thoſe Times, we hear no more of it till about the middle of the third Century; when it began again to be revived by <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſata.</hi> This <hi>Paul</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> and notorious for the abject, mean Opinion which he had of our Saviour, denying that the Word was ever truly u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited to the Humanity in the Perſon of Chriſt, and that he was ever any more but a meer Man. For the Suppreſſing of which Hereſie, and Cenſure of its Reviver, a Council was held at <hi>Antioch;</hi> where all the Paſtors of the Churches did aſſemble, only <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria</hi> was not there, which he excus'd by reaſon of his Age and Infirmity of Body: But he declar'd by Letter his Senſe and Opinion concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Matter in Debate.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59696:13"/>
            <p> At this Council there was aſſembled the moſt eminent Biſhops of thoſe Times, ſuch as <hi>Firmilianus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſaria</hi> in <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>padocia, Gregory</hi> and his Brother <hi>Athenodorus,</hi> Biſhops of the Churches of <hi>Pontus:</hi> There were alſo preſent <hi>Helenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tarſus, Nichomas</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Iconium, Hymenaeus</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem, Theotecnus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> on the Confines of <hi>Jeruſalem, Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> of <hi>Boſtra,</hi> together with many eminent Prieſts and Deacons. All theſe being aſſembled in the ſame Place, Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations and Queſtions were raiſed about the Hereſie of <hi>Paul:</hi> In all which he was obſerved to uſe great Art in concealing his heterodox Opinions, whilſt others were as diligent in finding them out and expoſing them. At laſt the Synod, which conſiſted of a very great Number of Biſhops, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed <hi>Paul,</hi> and unanimouſly condemn'd him of falſe Doctrine, and by Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, caſt him out of the Catholick Church. The deepeſt Wound the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick received in this Council was from <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio</hi> a Presbyter of the Church of <hi>Antioch,</hi> an eloquent Man, and one very famous for teaching the <hi>Grecian</hi> Philoſophy: He was alſo much taken Notice of for his ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Sincerity in the Chriſtian Faith. This <hi>Malchio</hi> having undertaken to diſpute a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59696:13"/>
               <hi>Paul,</hi> wonderfully detected and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed the Frauds and Sophiſtries of that crafty Heretick, by which and his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Virtues, <hi>Malchion</hi> gained ſuch a Credit and Renown, that he was thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to be canoniz'd in the <hi>Greek Meno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> at 28th of <hi>October.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prelates being aſſembled in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Antioch,</hi> they agreed upon ſending a Letter to <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to <hi>Maximus,</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Dionyſius</hi> in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> and having done this, they ſent the ſame Letter over all the Provinces; wherein they ſet down the pernicious and obſtinate Heterodoxy of <hi>Paul,</hi> the Confutations and Diſputes that had been held againſt him; together with a Narrative of his Life and Carriage. A Copy of which Epiſtle as it ſtands entire in <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and tranſlated at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I have thought not improper here to inſert.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:59696:14"/>
                  <head>The Synodical Epiſtle of the <hi>Antiochian</hi> Fathers, concerning <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſata,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by them for deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Divinity of Chriſt.</head>
                  <p>To <hi>Dionyſius</hi> and <hi>Maximus,</hi> and to all our Fellow-Miniſters over the whole World, Biſhops, Presbyters, and Deacons; and to the whole Catholick Church under Heaven, <hi>Helenus, Hymenaeus, Theophilus, Theotecnus, Maximus, Proclus, Nichomas, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lianus, Paul, Bolanus, Protogenes, Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erax, Eutychius, Theodorus, Malchion, Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> and all the Biſhops of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Cities and Provinces, which are with us; the Presbyters and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, and the Churches of God, to the beloved Bretheren in the Lord, Health.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE have written to, and entreated ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Biſhops far remote, that they would come to aſſiſt in the curing of this peſtilent Doctrine: For we wrote to</hi> Dionyſius <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Alexandria, <hi>and to</hi> Firmilianus <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Capadocia, <hi>Men of bleſſed Memory. The firſt of them wrote to</hi> Antioch; <hi>but did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſo much as vouchſafe the Author of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59696:14"/>Hereſie, a Salutation; neither did he write to him by Name, but to the whole Church: A Copy of which Letter, we have here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted. The other (to wit)</hi> Firmilianus, <hi>came twice, and condemned</hi> Paul<hi>'s Novelties, as we who were then preſent, do atteſt, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do alſo know as well as we. But when</hi> Paul <hi>promiſed to recant,</hi> Firmilianus <hi>believing him, and hoping that the Buſineſs might be compos'd without any Reproach to our Religion, he deferr'd his Sentence, being deceiv'd by him who denyed his God and Lord, and who kept not the Faith which he formerly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But</hi> Firmilianus <hi>was now coming to</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch, <hi>and came as far as</hi> Tarſus: <hi>For he had Experience of his malicious Wickedneſs, who denyed his God. But in the</hi> Interim <hi>of our Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling, and whilſt we were ſending for him, and expecting his Coming, he died.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But ſince that</hi> Paul <hi>has return'd to forg'd and ſpurious Opinions, departing from the true Rule, it is not our Concern to examine the Actions of one who is out of the Church; neither how he who was formerly poor and indigent (having no Eſtate of his Parents, nor got any thing by any Trade or Profeſſion) is now become incredibly rich, by his unlawful and ſacrilegious Dealings, by Extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Vexatiouſneſs, uſed towards the Brethren, and by taking Bribes from thoſe that were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jur'd,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59696:15"/>promiſing them to help them to their Right, for a Reward: But he deceiv'd them, getting Money for doing nothing, through their Willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (who were entangled in Suits) to give any thing to be delivered from thoſe Troubles. He ſuppoſed Gain to be Godlineſs: Neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare we how proud and inſolent this Hertick was, being inveſted with ſecular Dignities, and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be ſtiled a</hi> Ducenarius, <hi>rather than a Biſhop; and how he walked through the</hi> Forum, <hi>reading and dictating Letters as he walked in publick, with a numerous Guard about him, ſome going before and ſome following after him: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that there was an ill Opinion and an</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium <hi>brought upon the Faith, thro' his Pride and Haughtineſs. Neither does it concern us to examine his vain-glorious Ambition in the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick Conventions, which he greedily purſues being deſirous of Glory, and affected with an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary Pomp; with ſuch Devices as theſe, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying the Minds of the Faithful and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Beſides, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rected for himſelf a Tribunal, and a lofty Throne, not like one of Chriſt's Diſciples; but had a place called his</hi> Secretum, <hi>like as the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Magiſtrates have. He alſo uſed to clap his Hands upon his Thigh and ſtamp upon the Throne with his Feet: And ſuch as did not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him, and ſhake their</hi> Oraria <hi>as they uſually did in the Theatres, and did not make
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59696:15"/>loud Acclamations, nor leapt up and down in the ſame manner as his Favourites did (which were a Company of ſilly Men and Women that during their hearkening to him, uſed ſuch Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencies) but were attentive to him with ſuch a ſeemly Reverence and Decency as becomes the Houſe of God; thoſe Perſons he rebuk'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In his publick Diſcourſes he reflected upon the Doctors of our Religion that were dead, with all imaginable Scorn and Petulancy: But he magnified himſelf, not as became a Biſhop, but rather like a Counterfeit and an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He aboliſhed the Pſalms which were uſually ſung in Honour of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, as a Novel and the Compoſures of modern Men. On the great Feaſt of</hi> Eaſter, <hi>he appointed Women to ſing Pſalms in his Commendation in the Body of the Church; which whoſoever heard, might juſtly tremble at: He alſo privately ſent the Biſhops of the neighbouring Villages and Towns, and the Presbyters who were his Flatterers, to make Diſcourſes to the People in Commendati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him. He will not joyn in a Confeſſion with us, that the Son of God came down from Heaven; that we may premiſe ſome things of what we ſhall hereafter more at large de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in Writing: Neither ſhall this be affirmed on our bare Word, but it is evident in many
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59696:16"/>Places up and down his</hi> Acts, <hi>which we have ſent you. And more eſpecially where he ſays, that Jeſus Chriſt is of the Earth. But thoſe who chant out his Praiſe, and ſing his Encomiums amongſt the People, do ſay, that this their (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious) Maſter is an Angel come down from Heaven. Nor do's that haughty Fellow pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit thoſe Expreſſions, but is himſelf preſent when they are ſpoken.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What need we here mention his and his Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters and Deacons ſubintroduc'd</hi> Women <hi>(as the</hi> Antiochians <hi>term them) in whom he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceals, not only this, but many other damnable Crimes, which he is conſcious of, and of which he has been convicted, they are guilty; that by this means he may keep them ſo obnoxius as not to adventure through a Fear of their own Guilt, to accuſe him for his impious Words and Practices? Moreover he has enrich'd them, and for this Reaſon he is belov'd and admir'd by them who are covetous.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But why do we write theſe things? We know, (Beloved) that it is the Duty of a Biſhop, and of the whole Clergy, to be Examples of good Works to the People. Neither are we ignorant, that by introducing Women into their Society, ſome have wholly fallen away from Goodneſs, and others have been ſuſpected: And although it ſhould be granted that he committed nothing that was unchaſte, yet the very Suſpicion which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59696:16"/>from ſuch a thing, ought to be avoided, leſt it ſhould be offenſive to any one, and induce others to imitate it. For how can he reprove or admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh another not to frequent the Company of Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and to take heed leſt he fall, who indeed has ſent away one, but now keeps two that are young and beautiful, and carries them along with him wherever he goes, and indulges and ſtuffs himſelf with Delicacies?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe are the Reaſons that all People ſigh and lament privatly: But they ſo dread his Tyranny and Authority, that they dare not accuſe him. Now (as before we have ſaid) any one would call a Man, who profeſſes the Catholick Doctrine, and is reckoned of our Communion, to an Account for theſe things. But from one who has abjured the Myſtery of our Religion, and has boaſted in that curſed Hereſie of</hi> Artemon, <hi>we judge it need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to require an Account of theſe Things.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Having therefore excommunicated this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious Enemy of God, we are neceſſitated to ordain another Biſhop in his ſtead over the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church (as we are perſuaded not without the Providence of God) to wit</hi> Domnus <hi>(the Son of</hi> Demetrianus, <hi>of bleſſed Memory, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him was the eminent Governour of that See) a Man adorn'd with all Accompliſhments requiſite for a Biſhop; which we have therefore ſignified to you that you may write to him, and receive from him Communicatory Letters: But
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59696:17"/>as for this</hi> Paul, <hi>let him go to</hi> Artemon, <hi>if he pleaſes, and let the Followers of</hi> Artemon <hi>hold Communion with him.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This is the Circular Epiſtle which was compoſed and diſperſed by the ſecond <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochian</hi> Synod, which <hi>Baronius</hi> has placed at the Year of Chriſt 272. Seventy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſaith <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> were preſent at this Council, beſides Presbyters and Deacons, who did all unanimouſly concur in the Excommunication and Deveſtiture of <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſata;</hi> who according to what is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated in this Synodical Letter, was a Man of great Injuſtice and Avarice, and alſo of great Pride and ſuſpected Chaſtity. His Injuſtice and Covetouſneſs, were but too evident in the Methods which he uſed to make himſelf rich. His Extortion is par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly taken Notice of: Which he might commit, either by the Terror of his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, like Soldiers who fright and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Men, which was forbidden by our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: Or as he exerciſed Extortion by Deceit and Cunning, when under Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of favouring and helping Men, he took Bribes. And to this the Fathers of the Council in all Probability had reſpect, when they ſay that he did <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, extort the Brethren.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59696:17"/>
            <p> Next, his Pride was evident in his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious affecting to be called a <hi>Ducenarius,</hi> which was, an Officer appointed by the Emperour to collect and receive his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues; who for his Service, was allowed a yearly Salary of two hundred SESTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CES, and from thence had his Name <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenarius.</hi> The <hi>Antiochian</hi> Fathers take No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of this Heretick's Pride in his haughty and pompous walking through the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as that Word may ſignifie any promiſcuous or popular Aſſembly, met together, either for Traffick, as in a Fair or Market, or Hall, or Court of Judicature. Which Places, 'tis like, the vain-glorious Man frequented on purpoſe to receive the Acclamations of his Flatterers. His Pride appeared likewiſe in erecting of a lofty Throne. For although Epiſcopal Thrones were cuſtomary, even from the times of the Apoſtles as we may conclude from the Mention <hi>Euſebius</hi> makes of the Throne of <hi>James,</hi> Brother of the Lord; yet this Throne was no more than the Biſhop's Chair, which was but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle higher than the reſt of the Clergies: But <hi>Paul</hi> erected a Tribunal in the Church for himſelf, and ſate on a Seat higher than it was before. For though the Biſhops ever ſate ſomewhat higher than the reſt of the People, yet we find not that they had a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59696:18"/>This Piece of State was the peculiar Invention of <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtate, as was alſo the <hi>Secretum,</hi> or Place railed about in the inner Court, and hung with Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, where none ſate but the <hi>Judices majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res,</hi> or Judges of Life and Death; or ſuch as heard Trials of Criminals. And when <hi>Paul</hi> choſe to have ſuch a <hi>Secretum,</hi> it ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he was of an ambitious Spirit, and that he immoderately affected ſecular Grandeur, having rejected not only the Divinity of Chriſt, but alſo his Doctrine and Practice concerning Lowlineſs and Humility: For Vanity ſwell'd him ſo much, that on all Occaſions he courted Applauſe, and expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that thoſe who were Auditors of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, ſhould expreſs their Praiſe and Commendation of what he ſaid, by ſhaking their <hi>Oraria,</hi> or Handkerchiefs, as Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors did at Theatres, to declare their Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of what was acted.</p>
            <p>And to manifeſt yet further his inſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Thirſt of Praiſe, he privily excited the <hi>Chorepiſcopi,</hi> or Vicar-Biſhops, to make publick Diſcourſes and Harangues in his Commendation, and to extol his Merits and Government, in their Popular Meetings. But the infamous Carriage of this haughty Heretick was not bounded with filthy Lucre and vain Oſtentation; but it went on to a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59696:18"/>vehement Suſpicion of Incontinency with thoſe Women whom the <hi>Antiochians</hi> called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of which he had always with him thoſe that were young and beautiful, with whom he liv'd in great ſenſual De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights; as Feaſting, Drinking, and indulg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf in the common Incentives of Luſt. This ſort of Women are neither Wives nor Concubines, but ſuch as were kept by the Clergy upon a Pretence of Piety. <hi>Valeſius</hi> ſays, they were by ſome called <hi>Siſters,</hi> and by others <hi>Commanentes;</hi> becauſe they conſtantly abode with thoſe Presbyters and Deacons, who choſe them, as was pretended, not upon the Account of Luſt, but for Religion: And the Clergy of thoſe Times gave it out, they did this in Imitation of the Apoſtles, who carried Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men along with them whither ever they went to preach the Goſpel: Which Practice was founded upon thoſe Words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.5. But this Cuſtom of ſuperindu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Women, was condemned by the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod, and it is warmly inveighed againſt by <hi>Jerom.</hi> in his <hi>Ep.</hi> to <hi>Euſtochius.</hi> And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the leaſt of the mention'd Crimes, was in the purer Days of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Diſcipline, Ground enough to caſt any (guilty thereof, much more a Biſhop) out of the Communion of the Church;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59696:19"/>yet <hi>Paul,</hi> tho' he deſerv'd to be, was not cenſur'd for his Manners, but his Hereſie, in denying Chriſt to be God. And for a further Proof of the Pride and Obſtinacy of this ill Man, he ſlighted even Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and was ſo far from being humbled thereby, that he grew more inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent. For being Canonically excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and deprived by the <hi>Antiochian</hi> Fathers, he would not quit the Poſſeſſion of his Church but kept it for ſome Years after the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of being depoſed, was paſs'd againſt him, and would not obey the Decree of the Synod: But the better to fortifie his Contumacy, he put himſelf under the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of <hi>Zenobia,</hi> an Eaſtern Queen, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to whoſe Favour, by ſervile Flatteries, he had ſlily inſin uated himſelf. But when <hi>Zenobia</hi> was conquer'd, the Chriſtian Prelates petitioned <hi>Aurelianus,</hi> that this <hi>Paul,</hi> who had formerly conſpired with <hi>Zenobia</hi> againſt the <hi>Romans,</hi> might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from the See of <hi>Antioch.</hi> And <hi>Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus</hi> was at that time ſo well affected to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Chriſtians, that he granted their Requeſt, and gave Command that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Palace ſhould be reſigned to whom the Chriſtian Biſhops ſhould aſſign it by their Letters. Thus was the Heretick with great Diſgrace thruſt out of the Church by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59696:19"/>the ſecular Power, in the third Year of <hi>Aure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianus.</hi> It is remarkable that in the firſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Antioch, Paul</hi> ſeem'd to have recanted his Hereſie; but returning to it again, as a Dog to his Vomit, he was deprived by the Second, which was held on Purpoſe to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine and cenſure his Doctrine concerning Chriſt; which (ſaith the Council) was no other than what <hi>Annas</hi> and <hi>Caiphas</hi> taught concerning the <hi>Meſſias;</hi> namely, that <hi>he was to be the Son of God, no otherwiſe than by Favour and the divine Grace,</hi> that accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him after God had made choice of him to be the Saviour of Mankind.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſata</hi> being now ſuppreſs'd, his Hereſie was no more heard of till the Reign of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> who (having vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Collegue <hi>Licinius,</hi> and after put him to death upon his new Revolt) had Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand over the whole <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and being proclaim'd Emperor and <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> he endeavoured to augment the Affairs of the Chriſtians, who by his Means enjoyed a profound and ſecure Peace; which in all Probability might have continu'd, had not the Chriſtians fallen into inteſtine Wars among themſelves; which broke forth firſt in the Churches of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> occaſioned by a private Diſpute in the College there: But in a very ſhort Space (as <hi>Socrates</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves)
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59696:20"/>over-ran all <hi>Aegypt, Lybia</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bais,</hi> and the reſt of the Cities and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces. The Quarrel began thus. <hi>Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander</hi> who ſucceeded <hi>Achilles</hi> in the See of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> diſcourſing one Day in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of his Presbyters, and the reſt of his Clergy, too curiouſly concerning the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of the Holy <hi>Trinity,</hi> he aſſerted this Point of Divinity, That there was an Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in the <hi>Trinity.</hi> But <hi>Arius</hi> one of <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>'s Presbyters, being skilful in the Faculty of Reaſoning, ſuppoſed that the Biſhop deſigned to introduce the Opinion of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellius,</hi> who affirmed the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt to be but one Subſtance, one Perſon under three ſeveral Names: Which in the Time of the old Teſtament gave the Law under the Notion of the Father; In the New Teſtament was made Man, in the Capacity of the Son; and deſcended after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards upon the Apoſtles, in Quality of the Holy Ghoſt; which Opinion <hi>Dionyſius</hi> oppoſed with ſo much Eagerneſs and Warmth of Diſputation, that he bent it too much the contrary Way, aſſerting not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Diſtinction of
<q>
                  <hi>of Perſons in the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but alſo <hi>a Difference of Eſſence, an Ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality of Power and Glory.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For which <hi>Dionyſius</hi> was ſeverely cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as one of thoſe who in great
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59696:20"/>Meaſure opened a Gap to thoſe <hi>Arian</hi> Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieties, which afterwards broke into the Church. <hi>Arius</hi> (as <hi>Socrates</hi> obſerves) fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Opinion wholly oppoſite to that of <hi>Sabellius;</hi> not out of any Diſlike to <hi>Sabel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lianiſm,</hi> but only to oppoſe the Biſhop. He was of a perverſe and contentious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, and one that had too good an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his own Abilities. When <hi>Alexander</hi> gravely taught his Clergy, that there was an Unity in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> or, that the ſame nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merical Godhead was in every one of three Perſons of the Holy <hi>Trinity;</hi> what Lover of Truth and Peace would have excepted againſt it? And yet <hi>Arius</hi> a nimble ſharp <hi>Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant,</hi> flew in the Face of the Biſhop; and meerly out of a Spirit of Oppoſition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronts his Aſſertion of an Unity in the <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity:</hi> And from thence draws a Concluſion that was very remote and unnatural. For (according to <hi>Socrates) Arius</hi> argued thus:
<q>If the Father begot the Son, he that was begotten, hath a Beginning of his Exiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: And there was a time when the Son was not,</q> and by neceſſary Conſequence, he muſt derive his Exiſtence from nothing. This was the Form and Matter of <hi>Arius</hi>'s Argumentation, as <hi>Socrates</hi> relates it; which I leave the Logician to examine, only to obſerve, that this was no <hi>extempere</hi> or oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſional
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59696:21"/>Objection, brought by <hi>Arius</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt what had been diſcourſed by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; but the very Judgment and Thoughts which he had concerning the ſecond Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the <hi>Trinity,</hi> whom he held was not from Eternity, but took his being in Time, and was made of nothing, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in the Sequel of this Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>Now to ſhew that <hi>Arius</hi> did not draw his Concluſion only by way of Argument, but that it was his fix'd and reſolute Opinion, he preſently began to make Proſelytes, and to excite many to be of his Judgment: A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong whom, ſome think the firſt and chief was <hi>Euſebius,</hi> who had formerly been Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of the Church of <hi>Berytus;</hi> but was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reptitiouſly crept into the Biſhoprick of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comedia</hi> in <hi>Bithynia:</hi> And from this Spark (ſaith the Hiſtorian) was kindled a great Fire, many patronizing <hi>Arius</hi>'s Hereſie, and appearing in its Maintenance and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> hearing and ſeeing what was done, became highly incens'd, and having conven'd a Council of many Biſhops, he degraded <hi>Arius</hi> as an Heretick, and thoſe that embrac'd his Opinion; and gave the Biſhops of every City an Account of his Proceedings in a circular Letter; a Copy whereof as it ſtands in <hi>Socrates,</hi> now follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59696:21"/>
                  <head>A Copy of the Letter written by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to his Fellow-Biſhops, concerning the degrading of <hi>Arius.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">To our well-beloved and deareſt Fellow-Miniſters of the Catholick Church, in all Places, <hi>Alexander</hi> wiſhes Health in the Lord.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WHereas there is one Body of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church; and it is commanded in the holy Scriptures that we ſhould keep the Bond of Peace and Concord, it is requiſite that we ſhould write and inform one another of what things are done among us; to the end, that if one Member ſuffer, or rejoyce, we may either joyntly rejoyce, or ſuffer together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In our Dioceſs, therefore there are lately ſtarted up Men that are impious and Enemies of Chriſt, who teach ſuch Apoſtacy, as one may judge, and juſtly term the Fore-runner of Antichriſt, which I would moſt gladly have buried in Silence, that the Miſchief might have been conſumed, by being included among the Apoſtates only, leſt haply by its further Progreſs into other Places, it ſhould have infected the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> of the Simple.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59696:22"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>But becauſe</hi> Euſebius, <hi>now Biſhop of</hi> Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media, <hi>ſuppoſing that the Affairs are wholly at his Diſpoſe (in Regard, that having deſerted the Church of</hi> Berytus, <hi>he has ſordidly coveted that of</hi> Nicomedia, <hi>and has not been proſecuted by any) does patronize even theſe Apoſtates, and has boldly attempted to write Letters up and down in Commendation of them, that thereby he might ſeduce ſome Ignorant Perſons into this worſt Hereſie and moſt diſpleaſing to Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thought it therefore neceſſary, being ſenſible of what is written in the Law, to be no longer ſilent, but to give you all Notice, that you might know who are the Apoſtates, and likewiſe the deteſtable Expreſſions of their Hereſie, and that if</hi> Euſebius <hi>write to you, you ſhould give no Heed to him: For he is now deſirous to renew his former Malevolence, which ſeem'd to have been ſilenced and forgot by Length of Time, and pretends to write Letters in their Behalf: But in Reality he declares that he uſes his Utmoſt to do this upon his own Account.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Now the Names of thoſe that are turned A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtates, are theſe,</hi> Arius, Achilles, Aithales Carpones; <hi>Another</hi> Arius, Sarmates, Euzo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius, Lucius, Julianus, Menas, Helladius, Gaius, Secundus <hi>alſo and</hi> Theonas; <hi>who were ſometimes Biſhops: And the</hi> Tenets <hi>which they have invented and maintain'd, contrary to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59696:22"/>the Authority of Scripture, are theſe following,</hi> viz. <hi>God (they ſay) was not alway a Father; but there was a Time when God was not a Father. The Word of God was not from everlaſting; but had his Beginning from Nothing: For God who is, made him who was not, of Nothing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there was a Time when he was not: For the Son is a Creature, and Work: Neither is like to the Father, as to his Eſſence; nor is he by Nature the genuine Word of the Father, nor his true Wiſdom: But he is one of his Works, and one of his Creatures, and is only improperly ſtiled The</hi> Word <hi>and the</hi> Wiſdom: <hi>For he himſelf exiſts by the proper Word of God, and by the Wiſdom that is in God, by which God made all things, and him alſo: Wherefore he is by Nature mutable, and ſubject to Change, as well as all other rationable Beings: So that the Word is dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, diſagreeable and ſeparate from the Eſſence of God; and the Father cannot be declared or ſet forth by the Son, and is inviſible to him: For the Son does not perfectly and accurately know the Father; neither can he perfectly behold him: For the Son knows not his own Eſſence what it is: For our ſakes he was made, that God might make uſe of him as an Inſtrument in order to our Creation; nor had he ever exiſted, had it not pleaſed God to create us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>In this Heap of Blaſphemies are ſumm'd up the</hi> Dogmata <hi>of</hi> Arius <hi>and his Sectaries: And
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59696:23"/>when one ask'd them, if the Word of God could be chang'd as the Devil was, they were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to anſwer, that he might; becauſe he is (ſaid they) of a Nature ſubject to Change, in that he is begotten and created.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We, therefore, with the Biſhops of</hi> Egypt <hi>and</hi> Lybia, <hi>near an hundred in Number, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing met together, have Excommunicated</hi> Arius <hi>for theſe his Principles, and for his impudent Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion of them, together with all his Adherents: But</hi> Euſebius <hi>has given them Entertainment, endeavouring to mix Falſhood with Truth, and Impiety with Godlineſs: But he ſhall not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail: For Truth getteth the Victory; and Light has no Communion with Darkneſs; nor hath Chriſt any Agreemont with Belial. For who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard the like? or what Man, if he ſhould now hear them, would not be amaz'd thereat, and ſtop his Ears, leſt the Filth of thoſe Doctrines ſhould penetrate and infect them?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>What Man is he, who when he hears theſe Words of Saint</hi> John, In the Beginning was the Word, <hi>will not condemn thoſe that affirm There was a Time when the Word was not? Or who is the Man that hears theſe Words of the Goſpel,</hi> The only begotten Son, and by him all things were made, <hi>will not abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate theſe Men, that ſay, the Son is one of the Creatures? But how can he be one of thoſe Things that were made by him? Or, how can
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59696:23"/>he be term'd The</hi> only Begotten, <hi>who (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Sentiments of</hi> Arius) <hi>is reckon'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the other Creatures? How can he be made of Nothing, when as the Father himſelf ſaith, my Heart hath indited a good Matter: And, before the Morning, I have begotten thee in the Morning? Or, how can he be unlike the Father in Eſſence, when as he is the perfect I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and the Brightneſs of the Father; and when, as he himſelf teſtifieth, he that hath ſeen me, hath ſeen the Father? Now if the Son be the Word and Wiſdom of the Father, how can there be a Time when he was not? For it is the ſame Abſurdity as if they ſhould ſay, There was a Time when God was without both his Word and Wiſdom. How can he be mutable and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to Change, who ſays concerning himſelf, I am in the Father, and the Father in me, and I and the Father are one? I ſpake alſo by the Prophet, behold me, for I am the Lord, and am not changed: And tho' ſome may ſay, that this was ſpoken in Reference to the Father, yet it will be more accommodate to underſtand it now to be ſpoken in Relation to the Word; becauſe altho' he became Man, yet was he not chang'd; but as the Apoſtle ſays, Jeſus Chriſt the ſame Yeſterday, and to Day, and for ever. But what Motive could they have to ſay, that he was made for us, when as</hi> Paul <hi>ſaith, for him are all things, and by him are all things?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:59696:24"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>But concerning their Blaſphemy in affirming that the Son doth not perfectly know the Father, it ought not to be wondred at: For having once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to fight againſt Chriſt, they deſpiſe even the Words of the Lord himſelf; who ſays, as the Father knoweth me, even ſo know I the Father. If therefore the Father knoweth the Son only in Part, it is manifeſt, that the Son alſo knoweth the Father only in part: But if it be impious to aſſert this, and if the Father knoweth the Son perfectly, it is perſpicuous, that as the Father knoweth his own Word, ſo doth the Word know his own Father, whoſe Word he is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By aſſerting of theſe things, and explaining the ſacred Scriptures, we have frequently confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them: But they, like</hi> Chamaelions, <hi>have again been chang'd, pertinaciouſly contending to appropriate to themſelves this that is written: When the Impious is arrived at the very Extreams of Wickedneſs he deſpiſeth. There have indeed been many Hereſies before theſe Perſons, which by their too much Audaciouſneſs have fallen into Imprudence and Folly: But theſe Men, who by all their Diſcourſes, attempt nothing leſs than the Subverſion of the Divinity of the Word, have to the utmoſt of their Power, made thoſe preced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Hereſies to be accounted juſt, in regard they approach nearer to Antichriſt: Wherefore they are expell'd out of the Church, and anathematiz'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We are really troubl'd at the Deſtruction of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59696:24"/>theſe Men, and the rather becauſe they were heretofore inſtructed in the Doctrine of the Church, but have now renounc'd it: Yet we do not look upon this as ſo ſtrange a Thing: For the ſame befell</hi> Hymenaeus <hi>and</hi> Philetus, <hi>and before</hi> them, Judas; <hi>who tho' he had been our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's Diſciple, yet was afterwards his Betrayer and an Apoſtate. Neither have we continu'd unadvis'd of theſe very Perſons: For our Lord hath foretold,</hi> Take heed that no Man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you: For many ſhall come in my Name, ſaying, I am Chriſt: And the time draweth near, and they ſhall deceive many: Go ye not therefore after them. <hi>And</hi> Paul <hi>having learn'd theſe things from our Saviour, wrote thus;</hi> That in the latter Days, ſome ſhall depart from the ſound Faith, giving heed to ſeducing Spirits and Doctrines of Devils, who deteſt the Truth. <hi>Since there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt hath himſelf commanded this, and alſo by his Apoſtle has given us Intimation concerning theſe, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eye-witneſſes of their Impiety, have deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly anathematiz'd them, as we ſaid before and openly declar'd them eſtrang'd from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church and Faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moreover we have ſignified thus much to your Piety, (Beloved and deareſt Fellow-Miniſters) that if any of them ſhould have the Confidence to come to you, you might not entertain them, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59696:25"/>that you ſhould not be perſuaded to believe</hi> Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius, <hi>or any one elſe that ſhall write to you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them: For it is our Duty, as we are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to deteſt all thoſe that ſpeak or deviſe any thing againſt Chriſt, and to look upon them as the Enemies of God, and the Corrupters of Souls, and not to ſay to ſuch Men, ſo much as God ſpeed, leſt we become Partakers of their I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niquities (as St.</hi> John <hi>has commanded us) ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the Brethren that are with you; they that are with us, ſalute you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander</hi> having writ after this Manner to all the Biſhops in every City, the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance of his Letters was very different: Thoſe of his Opinion receiv'd them with great Reſpect, and readily ſubſcrib'd to their Contents, praiſing his Zeal and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct in ſo important an Affair: But o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers did the quite contrary, ſcoffing at and ridiculing what he writ; and inſtead of being thereby ſtir'd up to Peace, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be enflam'd with a pertinacious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Contention: So that as <hi>Socrates</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, the Miſchief grew worſe, and the Diſeaſe was encreas'd by the Miſapplication of the Remedy, deſign'd to cure it. <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> appear'd moſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Letter, as finding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf therein mention'd by Name, and not
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59696:25"/>without a particular Mark of Reproach. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> at the ſame time kept his Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence at <hi>Nicomedia</hi> in the Palace which <hi>Diocleſian</hi> had built there, which gave <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> an Opportunity of making an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in him: And being a ſmooth ſubtle Courtier, he quickly gain'd his Point and grew very gracious with the Emperour; which the Court-Biſhops obſerving, they became very obſequious to <hi>Euſebius,</hi> who writ frequently to <hi>Alexander,</hi> adviſing him to ſuppreſs the Controverſie, and to reſtore <hi>Arius</hi> and his Adherents to the Peace of the Church. He wrote likewiſe to Biſhops of every particular City, that they ſhould not conſent to <hi>Alexander.</hi> This occaſion'd great Animoſities, and fill'd all Places with Tumults and Diſturbances; and not only the Prelates of the Church, but the Populace alſo were miſerably divided, ſome inclining to one Party, and ſome to another; and the Matter at length came to that Height of Indignity and Inſolence, that the Chriſtian Religion was made the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicule in the publick Theatres. <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſtill preſs'd <hi>Alexander</hi> to abrogate the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Excommunication that had been pronounc'd againſt <hi>Arius</hi> and his Party, and to re-admit them into the Church, alledging that they aſſerted nothing that was perverſe
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59696:26"/>and impious. On the other Hand, thoſe who look'd upon the Opinion of <hi>Arius</hi> as abſurd and blaſphemous, approv'd of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>'s Proceedings, maintaining the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation of <hi>Arius,</hi> and of all that favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Hereſie, to be juſt and equitable, and that his Sentence out ght not to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed.</p>
            <p>Many Letters from both the diſagreeing Parties having been ſent to the Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> there was a Collection made of them. <hi>Arius</hi> collected thoſe that were written in his Behalf, and <hi>Alexander</hi> thoſe that were writ againſt him: And by this Example, all other Sects took Occaſion of defending their own Heterodox Opinions, each quoting the Epiſtles of their own Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that had been written in Confirmation of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſtantine</hi> having Notice of theſe things, was greatly troubled, and look'd upon this calamitous State of the Church as if it had been his own; and it did not a little perplex his Mind, that that Tranquility he had provided for the Chriſtians, ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed by themſelves: And foreſeeing that the Miſchiefs of theſe Contentions, if let alone, would daily grow worſe, he inſtantly made it his Buſineſs to ſuppreſs them. To this End, he ſent <hi>Hoſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Corduba</hi> in
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59696:26"/>
               <hi>Spain,</hi> a Perſon of approved Fidelity, and one for whom the Emperour had a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Kindneſs and Eſteem, with Letters to <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arius.</hi> In theſe Letters the Emperour ſets down the Ground of the Controverſie; and beginning with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> he reproves him for enquiring of his Presbyters what every Man's Opinion was, concerning a Point which he called a fruitleſs Controverſie: Next he blames <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> for his inconſiderate venting ſuch Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents as he ought either not to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd at all, or if he had had ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions, yet it was his Duty not to have divulg'd them; but to have buried them in Silence. He told them how that by their Diſſention, Communion was refuſed; and that the moſt religious Populace was rent into two Factions, and ſeparated from the harmonius Unity of the whole Body; and upon this Conſideration, he adviſes them mutually to pardon each other, and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to accept of what he as their Fellow-Servant, did lovingly counſel them. He tells the Biſhop that he ought not to have propounded the Queſtion which firſt occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the Diſpute; and he told the Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, that he ought not to have been ſo forward in returning an Anſwer. Such Queſtions (ſaith the Emperour) as no
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59696:27"/>Law does neceſſarily limit or preſcribe, but are propos'd by Contentiouſneſs, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable Want of Buſineſs (altho' they may be fram'd to exerciſe and employ our natural Parts) yet they ought to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd within our Breaſts, and not to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderately divulg'd in publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, nor unadviſedly committed to the Cares of the Vulgar: For what Perſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a thouſand is ſufficiently qualified either accurately to comprehend the full Efficacy and Nature of things ſo ſublime and profound, or, to explain them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Dignity and Importance? Or if any ſhould look upon this to be an eaſie Performance, yet how ſmall a Number of Vulgar will be induc'd to be fully perſuad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereof? Beſides, a Man of Prudence will not venture upon the accurate Diſcuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſuch nice Controverſies, for fear he ſhould fall into groſs Errors.</p>
            <p>In Queſtions of this Nature (ſaith the Emperour) Loquacity muſt be bridled, and the multiplying of Words reſtrained; leſt thro' our own Inability to explain ſuch ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Points; or thro' the Slowneſs of the Auditors underſtanding clearly to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what we diſcourſe, they ſhould unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily fall into Blaſphemy and Schiſm.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:59696:27"/>
            <p> Wherefore <hi>Conſtantine</hi> would have an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Queſtion, and an inconſiderate An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer by both of them to be mutually for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given. The Conteſt (as he tells them) was not kindled upon Occaſion of any principal or chief Commandment of our Law: Neither had they introduc'd any new Hereſie concerning the Worſhip of God: But that they both held one and the ſame Opinion: So that they might eaſily cloſe in a Conſent of Communion with each other. But whilſt they pertinaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contended about things of inferiour Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it was not convenient that ſo great Numbers of God's People ſhould be under their Care and Government, leſt thro' their Diſſention they ſhould be miſ-led as look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon it, not only as undecent, but alſo unlawful.</p>
            <p>And the Emperour inforces his Advice to Peace by the Example of the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers, who albeit they frequently diſagree in ſome Part of their Aſſertions, and jar about the very Perfection of Knowledge yet becauſe they are all united, and agree in the Profeſſion of one and the ſame Sect, they do again cloſe in mutual Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>Now if it be ſo amongſt Philoſophers, it will certainly be much more reaſonable
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59696:28"/>that thoſe who are Miniſters of the moſt high God, ſhould in like manner be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimous in the Profeſſion of the ſame Religion.</p>
            <p>Can you think it to be juſt and equita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that by Reaſon of your pertinacious Contraſts about Words, Brethren ſhould be ſet in Array againſt Brethren, and that that venerable Aſſembly (meaning either the Council or the Church) ſhould upon your Account who contend with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother about things ſlight, and no way ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, be rent in ſunder by an impious Variance? Theſe your Conteſts (ſaith the Emperour) are poor and mean, fitter for a childiſh Ignorance, than the Gravity of Prieſts and the Wiſdom of prudent Men. Be content to depart from the Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Satan: And conſider that our great God, the Saviour of all Men, hath reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth a Light, common to all. By the Aſſiſtance of whoſe Providence, give us Leave who are his Servants, ſucceſsfully to finiſh this our Endeavour, that by our Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortaion, Diligence and earneſt Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, we may reduce you to Unity, and bring you back to the ſame Communion: For ſeeing you hold the ſame Faith, and have the ſame Sentiments of Religion: And ſeeing the Commandment of the Law
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59696:28"/>doth in all its Parts encloſe all in general in one Conſent and Purpoſe of Mind, let not this thing that has rais'd a mutual Diviſion betwixt you in a Point not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to the Power and Efficacy of Religion in general, by any Means make a Separation and Faction amongſt you.</p>
            <p>We ſpeak theſe things (ſaith the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour) not to force you to be all of one O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion concerning this idle fooliſh Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie, of what ſoever it be: For the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Value of the Aſſembly may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved entire amongſt you; and one of the ſame Communion may be retain'd, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' there may be amongſt you a great Diverſity of Sentiments in things of ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler Significancy: For we don't all mean the ſame in all things; neither is there one Diſpoſition or Opinion in us all. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the divine Providence; let there be among you one Faith, one Meaning and one Covenant of the Deity. But as for theſe ſlender and light Queſtions, which with ſo much Niceneſs you diſpute of, and with too great Curioſity enquire into, tho' you are not therein of the ſame Mind, but diſagree in Opinion, yet it's your Duty to confine them to your own Thoughts, and to keep them to your ſelves. And upon this Conſideration, he exhorts them
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59696:29"/>to common Friendſhip, to a cordial Belief of the Truth, to promote the Honour of God, and to a Religious Obſervance of the Law; that they would let thoſe things remain firm and inviolable amongſt them, that they would return to mutual Amity and Charity, and to reſtore to the whole Body of the People their mutual amicable Embraces, that the Contenders would pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie their own Souls, be again acquainted, and renew their Familiarity one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to revolve with themſelves how that Friendſhip is often more ſweet and pleaſant after the Occaſion of the Enmity is laid aſide, and Men return again to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation.</p>
            <p>The Emperour having thus preſs'd <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> and <hi>Arius</hi> to mutual Friendſhip, and to put away their Contentions as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hurtful to themſelves and the Church, he likewiſe exhorts them to do this for the Emperor's Sake, that his Days thereby might be peaceable, and his Nights void of Solicitude, that during the Reſidue of his Life he might have the Pleaſure of a pure Light, and the Joy of a quiet Life reſerved for him; and that if he miſs'd of this, he muſt neceſſarily be griev'd, and teſtifie the ſame with Tears: For whilſt he beheld the People rent aſunder by
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59696:29"/>the pernicious and indiſcreet Diſſention of a Biſhop and a Presbyter, and engag'd in their undecent and untimely Quarrel, he tells them he could not continue in a ſedate Temper of Mind, nor finiſh his Life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great Diſquietude: And that they might be the more ſenſible of his great Sorrow and deep Reſentment for their Diviſions, he further tells them, that it had put by his Journey, which upon his coming to <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> he had reſolved to make into the Eaſt: And that whilſt he was haſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing towards them, and had perform'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove half his Journey, the News of their Diſcord quite alter'd his Reſolution, leſt he ſhould be a Spectator of thoſe things which he could not endure ſo much as to hear of. And the pious <hi>Conſtantine</hi> cloſes his Letter to <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arius</hi> in theſe affectionate Words;
<q>Do you by your U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity for the future, open a Way for us into the Eaſt, which by your Diſcord you have ſtopt up Give me Leave with Joy ſpeedily to ſee you and all the reſt of the People, and that with an unanimous Conſent of Praiſes we may offer up (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) to God Thanks for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Unity, Agreement, Liberty and Concord.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:59696:30"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Victor Conſtantinus Maximus Auguſtus</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent this Letter to <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Arius,</hi> when the Contents of it came to be fully conſidered, it was ſhrewdly ſuſpected that <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> had a Hand in the Contrivance of it, if it was not wholly compil'd by him: And the Circumſtances favouring this Conjecture, were, firſt, the great Credit <hi>Euſebius</hi> gain'd with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror now reſiding at <hi>Nicomedia;</hi> by Means of which he was able, as he did, to impoſe upon him in this whole Affair. Next, the Scope of the Letter is exactly agreeable with the Carriage of <hi>Euſebius</hi> in this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, which was, not to have it determined either Way; but only ſilenc'd as an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curious Speculation: And as for thoſe Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenings, which through the whole Letter are given of this Hereſie, they ſeem to have been the crafty Inſinuations of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Want of Temper and Prudence in raiſing ſo great a Duſt, and making ſo much ado in ſo trivial and light a Matter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> (as all obſerve of him) was a Man of a prou'd Spirit, impatient of Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, very vindictive, and cou'd not brook <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Carriage towards him: And the Hatred he bore him for his reproachful nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him in his circular Letter, made him favour <hi>Arius</hi> as he was <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Enemy,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59696:30"/>and not out of any good Liking he had for his Hereſie: For tho' <hi>Euſebius</hi> is on all Hands repreſented as a Ring-Leader of the <hi>Arian</hi> Faction, yet this is a Miſtake that has brought Confuſion upon the whole Hiſtory, and made the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie to ſeem of much greater Extent than it was: Whereas <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> and his Party were no leſs adverſe to the <hi>Arians</hi> than to the Orthodox; and yet it was they that all along made the greateſt Shew and Noiſe in the Conteſt: All which ſeems to have had no other Source than meerly their Hatred to <hi>Alexander,</hi> and the Delight they took to oppoſe him.</p>
            <p>The Emperour having, as he thought, by this Letter, made Proviſion for the ending of the Controverſie, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciling thoſe to each other, by whom it was firſt raiſed; and the good Man <hi>Hoſius</hi> who carried it, having uſed likewiſe his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt Diligence that the ſame Letter ſhou'd take Effect, yet all was to no Purpoſe: For the Contention of the diſagreeing Parties was ſo far from being compromis'd, that it daily encreas'd and grew up ſo faſt, that in a ſhort time it over-ran all the Eaſtern Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces: For Envy and the malicious De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil being vex'd at the Proſperity of the Church, invented theſe things for our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59696:31"/>Deſtruction, as <hi>Euſebius</hi> writes <hi>de Vitâ Conſt. B.</hi> 3. <hi>Ch.</hi> 73. But neither <hi>Alexander</hi> nor <hi>Arius</hi> were in the leaſt mollified, either by the Emperour's Letter, or the excellent Arguments for their mutual Agreement, urged by the holy Man that brought it. At the time when this Epiſtle was ſent, the Diſputes about the Feaſt of <hi>Eaſter</hi> were very warm, and the Diviſion ariſing thereupon very threatning. Some contended that the Celebration of that Feſtival ſhou'd be kept after the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Manner; others in their Solemnization thereof imitated the Cuſtom of the Chriſtians all over the World. But it was very happy this Controverſie happened only in the Eaſt, and that it created no Separation, but that the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe Parties ſtill continu'd united in the ſame Communion: For tho' the Joy and Glory of the Feſtival was much clouded, and impaired by the Controveſies held about it, yet mutual Communion was ſtill preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But <hi>Conſtantine</hi> obſerving the great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance that the Church ſuffered by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this and the other Controverſie, began to think of a Remedy for them both. He had already ſeen that his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were ineffectual to this Purpoſe, and that the Minds of the Contenders were ſo imbittered one againſt another, that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:59696:31"/>to mutual Peace and good Will, had little other Effect than to enrage and enflame them the more. He therefore thought of a general Council, as the likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Cure for ſuch Diſtempers. <hi>Nice,</hi> a City of <hi>Bithynia,</hi> was the Place where he deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined the Council ſhou'd be held: And hither by his Letters he requeſts the Biſhops to repair; who readily comply'd with his royal Requeſt: For (as <hi>Euſebius</hi> in the third Book of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> writes) the moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent amongſt God's Miniſters of the Churches in <hi>Europe, Lybia</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> were conven'd: And one ſacred Oratory, enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged as it were by God, included at the ſame time within its Walls, <hi>Sirians, Sileſians, Phoenicians, Arabians, Paleſtinians, Aegyptians, Thebaeans, Lybians,</hi> and thoſe that came out of <hi>Meſopotamia.</hi> There was alſo at the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod a <hi>Perſian</hi> and a <hi>Scythian: Pontus</hi> alſo and <hi>Galatia, Pamphilia, Cappadocia, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Phrygia</hi> afforded their moſt ſelect Divines. Moreover there appeared at <hi>Nice, Thracians, Macedonians, Achaians</hi> and <hi>Epirots.</hi> And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny who dwelt far beyond theſe, were there alſo preſent. <hi>Hoſius</hi> the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> famous for his Piety, together with many of his Country-men, ſate in the Council. The Prelate of the Imperial City was abſent by reaſon of his Age; but his Presbyters were there, and ſupply'd his Place.</p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:59696:32"/>
            <p> The Emperour (ſaith the Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher) was the only Perſon of all the Princes ſince the Foundation of the World, who having platted ſuch a Crown as this with the Bond of Peace, dedicated it to Chriſt his Saviour, as a Divine Preſent and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of the Victories he had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained over his Enemies. And he intended the Synod ſhou'd be conſtituted to be a live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Repreſentation of an Apoſtolical Quire: That it might be now as it was in the Days of the Apoſtles when devout Men of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions under Heaven were gathered together. In this Council the Number of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops exceeded Three Hundred: But the Presbyters, Deacons, <hi>Acoluthi,</hi> and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Perſons that accompanied them, were almoſt innumerable. Of theſe Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God, ſome were eminent for their Wiſdom and Eloquence; others for their ſober and diſcreet Lives; others for their patient Sufferings, and others were adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Modeſty and courteous Behaviour; Some of them were highly reſpected for their great Age; others were eminent for their youthful Vigour both of Body and Mind; ſome were newly initiated into the Order of the Miniſtry. To all theſe the Emperour commanded a plentiful Proviſion of Food to be daily allowed.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:59696:32"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Paphnutius</hi> and <hi>Spiridion</hi> were the moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent among the Biſhops. There were alſo preſent a great many Laicks, Men skill'd in Logick, ready to aſſiſt each their own Party. <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia, Theognis,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nice,</hi> and <hi>Maris</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Chalce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in <hi>Bithynia</hi> were the chief that favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Arius;</hi> againſt whom <hi>Athanaſius</hi> contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vigourouſly, and expreſs'd a ſignal Zeal and Depth in his Diſputes; which brought upon him the implacable Hatred of <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia.</hi> A little before the Biſhops were met together in one Place, the Logi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians exerciſed themſelves in ſome skirmiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſputes; and ſeeming therewith to be over-much delighted, a Laick, one that was a Confeſſour, an honeſt well-meaning Man, oppoſed theſe Diſputants, and told 'em, That neither Chriſt nor his Apoſtles taught or uſed the Art of Diſputing, nor vain Subtilties or Fallacies, but a plain Doctrin, which is to be defended by Faith and good Works. All that ſtood by, hearing him ſpeak theſe Words, admired him, and approved of what he ſaid: And the Logicians themſelves hearing this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and plain Declaration of the Truth, did patiently acquieſce, and the Tumult, raiſed by Diſputation, was compoſed.</p>
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:59696:33"/>
            <p> The next Day after the Logick Diſputes were ſo happily concluded, all the Biſhops were conven'd, after whom came the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, whoſe Reſpect and Reverence was ſo great to the Clergy, that he ſtood in the midſt of them, and wou'd not take his Seat, till ſuch time as the Biſhops ſignified that it was their Deſire that he wou'd ſit down and take the Chair of State; which he did, and from thence ſpoke to the Synod in kind perſuaſive Words; exhorting 'em to Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity and Concord, and to ſuppreſs all private Piques and Animoſities, and thoſe Accuſations which they had fram'd one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another: For many, the Day before, had preſented Libels to the Emperour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſeveral Articles of Perſonal Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriges, ſavouring more of a Deſire of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge than of Reformation. Theſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatory Libels the Emperour commanded to be burn'd, and advis'd them to conſider and obey what Chriſt had enjoyn'd con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning forgiving one another: And hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing largely diſcourſed of the Nature and Advantages of Concord and Peace, he bid 'em proceed to the Buſineſs before 'em, for which they were conven'd, leaving it, to their Power and Arbitrement accurately to inſpect the Points in Controverſie. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this the Council entred upon the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59696:33"/>and many Queſtions were propoſed by both Parties, which cauſed great Stirs and Heats before they came to the main Debate. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> all the while heard 'em very patiently, and with an intent Mind received their propoſed Queſtions, and by turns aſſiſted the Aſſertions of both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and by Degrees he reduced them, who pertinaciouſly oppoſed each other, to a more ſedate Temper of Mind; and by his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Speeches to each Perſon, he ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred himſelf pleaſing and delightful. Some he brought to be of his Opinion by the Force of his Arguments; others he gained over to him by Condeſcentions and Entreaties. He commended thoſe that ſpoke well, and whom he obſerved to be leſs peaceably enclined, he excited to Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſs, and conjur'd all to an Agreement: And by his prudent and temperate Manage, he at length made 'em all of the ſame Mind in the Matters concerning which they had before diſagreed: So that after many Debates upon the Subject before 'em, Three Hundred and Eighteen Biſhops concurr'd in a Creed, which with loud Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations they publiſhed and approv'd of. A Copy of which Creed, as it ſtands recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by <hi>Socrates Scholaſticus, Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 8. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ.</hi> now follows.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:59696:34"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>WE believe in one God, the Father Almighty, Maker of all things viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and inviſible, and one Lord Ieſus Chriſt the Son of God, begotten of the Father, the only Begotten, that is of the Subſtance of the Father, God of God and Light of Light, very God of very God, begotten, not made, of the ſame Subſtance with the Father, by whom all things were made that are in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and in Earth: VVho for the ſake of us Men, and for our Salvation, deſcended, and was incarnate, and was made Man, and he ſuffered and roſe again the third Day, aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Heavens, he ſhall come to judge the Dick and the Dead. VVe alſo believe in the Holy Ghoſt. But the holy Catholick and Apoſtolick Church doth anathematize thoſe that averr, That there was a time when the Son of God was not, and that he was not before he was begotten, and that he was made of Nothing: Or, that ſay he was made of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Subſtance or Eſſence: Or, that he is either created, or convertible, or mutable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Creed (as <hi>Valeſius</hi> obſerves) is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all the <hi>Mss.</hi> he had met with, and ſaith that <hi>Chriſtopherſon</hi> did very well in plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it here in <hi>Socrates:</hi> For it is plain, both from <hi>Epiphanius Scholaſticus,</hi> as alſo by thoſe
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59696:34"/>following Words, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that it was placed here by the Hiſtorian himſelf. But all the <hi>MSS.</hi> did omit it in this Place, becauſe it's repeated a little after in <hi>Euſebius Pamphilus</hi>'s Epiſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Then this very Creed above repeated, was ſubſcribed by Three Hundred and Eighteen Biſhops, who were all unanimous in their Suffrages and Sentiments concerning it. <hi>Socrates</hi> writes, that Five Biſhops refus'd to allow of it: But <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and before him <hi>Hierom,</hi> (in his Dialogue againſt the <hi>Luciferians</hi>) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, that <hi>Secundus</hi> and <hi>Theonas</hi> were the only two Biſhops that were Diffenters, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to ſubſcribe to the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed. <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia,</hi> with four Biſhops more, diſlik'd the Word <hi>Homoouſios,</hi> which they did upon Suppoſal that only that can be ſaid to be <hi>Homoouſion, of the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> which is from another; either by Partition, as two or three Pieces of Gold the whole Maſs; or, by Derivation, as Children from their Parents; or, by Erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as a Branch from the Root. But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Son of God could by none of theſe Ways be from the Father, they cou'd not therefore give Conſent to this Draught of the Creed, in which the Word <hi>Homoouſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os</hi> was uſed. Great and tedious were the Cavils and Debates about this one Word <hi>Homoouſios,</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:59696:35"/>which <hi>Euſebius</hi> and his Party would by no Means admit of; and becauſe it was not eras'd out of the Creed, they refuſed to ſubſcribe the Degradation of <hi>Arius;</hi> which Obſtinacy of theirs mov'd the Synod to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathematize <hi>Arius</hi> and all of his Opinion; forbidding <hi>Arius</hi> in particular to enter into <hi>Alexandria.</hi> The Emperour alſo by his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict, baniſh'd <hi>Arius, Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis:</hi> But the two latter ſoon after their Exile re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of their Contumacy, and ſent their penitentiary Libels to the moſt eminent Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops; and in theſe Libels they declared their Aſſent to the Word <hi>Homoouſios,</hi> and their Belief of it as it was uſed in the Creed, and in every thing agreed to the Expoſition of the Faith: And upon their doing this, they were by Imperial Order recalled from Baniſhment, and reſtored to their own Churches.</p>
            <p>At the ſame time, <hi>Euſebius,</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Pamphilus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made ſome Heſitancy in the Synod, whether he might ſafely admit of this Form of Faith; having taken time maturely to conſider what in this Caſe he might with a ſafe Conſcience and a ſatisfied Reaſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, he at length gave his Aſſent, and ſubſcribed. And leſt any of the People of his Dioceſs ſhou'd be offended at his Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59696:35"/>in ſubſcribing the Creed, and have an Ill Opinion of him for ſcrupling the Uſe of the Word <hi>Homoouſios,</hi> he ſent a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter unto them, wherein he explained that Term, and apologiz'd for his Heſitancy.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Euſebius Pamphilus<hi>'s Letter to thoſe of his Dioceſs.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IT is very probable (Beloved) that you may have heard what hath been done concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Eccleſiaſtick Faith in the great Council conven'd at</hi> Nice, <hi>and in Regard that Report doth uſually out-run an accurate Narrative of the Matters tranſacted, leſt by ſuch a bare Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, the Matter might be repreſented to you otherwiſe than really it is, we thought it requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to ſend to you, firſt, the Form of Faith which we our ſelves propoſed to the Council; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe that other publiſhed by the Biſhops, who made ſome Additions to ours. That Form of Faith drawn up by us, we read in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of our moſt pious Emperour; and it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to all to be ſound and Orthodox, and is as follows.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:59696:36"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>WE believe in one God, the Father Almighcy, Maker of all things, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inviſible, and in one Lord Ieſus Chriſt, the Word of God, God of God, Light of Light, Life of Life, the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Son, the firſt born of every Creature begotten of God the Father before all Worlds, by whom alſo all things were move; who for our Salvation was incarnate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers'd among Men; who ſuffered and roſe again the third Day; he aſcended unto the Father, and ſhall come again in Glory to judge the Quick and the Dead.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVe alſo believe in the Holy Ghoſt: we believe that each of theſe Perſons is, and doth ſubſiſt: That the Father is truly the Father, the Son really the Son, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt really the Holy Ghoſt: As our Lord alſo when he ſent his Diſciples out to preach, ſaid, Go ye, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt. Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which Articles, we do averr, that we thus maintain and hold them, that theſe are our Sentiments of them, that this was our Opinion formerly, that this Opinion we will retain till Death, that we we will perſevere in this Belief, and anathematize every im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious</hi> Hereſie: <hi>VVe call God Almighty and
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59696:36"/>Ieſus Chriſt our Lord to VVitneſs, that theſe were ſincerely and heartily our Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ever ſince we were capable of knowing our ſelves: And that we do now ſpeak and think what is moſt true, and we are ready to demonſtrate to you by moſt infallible Proofs and to perſuade you, that both in times paſt, we thus believed and likewiſe thus preached.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius Pamphilus</hi> having given the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his Dioceſs this Account of the Creed which he propoſed to the Council, he farther tells 'em, That there was no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy could oppoſe it: That the Emperour did atteſt its Truth, proteſting that he was of the ſame Opinion, and exhorted all to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to, and ſubſcribe it, and unanimouſly to agree in the Profeſſion of it. Only he deſired that the Word <hi>Homoouſios</hi> might be inſerted; tho' others with greater Probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity affirm, that that Word was added by the Biſhops, and that the Emperour explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, ſaying, that he ſuppoſed that the Word <hi>Homoouſios</hi> was not to be taken in ſuch a Senſe as is agreeable to the Affections of the Body and therefore that the Son had not his Subſiſtence from the Father, either by Diviſion or Abſciſſion: For it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible (ſaith he) that an immaterial intelle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59696:37"/>and incorporeal Nature ſhou'd be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to any corporeal Affection: But that our Sentiments of ſuch things ſhould be expreſſed in Divine and Myſterious Terms.</p>
            <p>The Emperour having thus Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed upon the Word <hi>Homoouſios,</hi> the Biſhops drew up another Form of Belief, in which they inſerted that <hi>Word;</hi> but in all other things it was the ſame with the firſt. Now that the Form of Faith was agreed upon by the Biſhops, <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſes</hi> gravely and maturely enquired of them What they meant by theſe Words, [Of the Subſtance of the Father, and of the ſame Subſtance with the Father;] Which gave Occaſion to many Queſtions and Anſwers, and to an accurate Examination of the Importance of the Words. And at laſt it was acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg'd by the Biſhops that theſe Words, <hi>To be of the Subſtance</hi> did only ſignifie thus much: That the Son is of the Father, but not as a Part of the Father. To which Senſe of the Words <hi>Euſebius Caeſarienſis</hi> thought it both reaſonable and ſafe to give his Aſſent: And having Peace before his Eyes, as the Mark at which he aim'd, and being cautious leſt he ſhould fall from a right Apprehenſion of the Faith, he alſo admitted of the Words <hi>Begotten not made,</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:59696:37"/>For <hi>Made</hi> (ſaid the Fathers) is a common Term attributed to all other Creatures which were made by the Son, of whom the Son hath no Reſemblance. Wherefore he is no Creature like thoſe which were created by him; but he is of a far more excellent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance than any Creature: Which Subſtance is begotten of the Father, but in ſuch a Manner of Generation as is ineffable and inexpreſſible by any created Being: For, his Generation, who ſhall be able to declare? Who can expreſs how he was eternally be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten? Who can explain of ſet forth his Divine Extraction? No Man knoweth the Son but the Father. That Light that ſhone before the World, that Intellectual and Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Wiſdom that was before all Ages, the living God; the Word who was in the the Beginning with the Father, who, but the Father alone can clearly and perfectly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend? The Propoſition that ſaith, The Son is of the ſame Subſtance with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, being alſo diſcuſs'd; <hi>Euſebius Caeſ.</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that it was not to be underſtood ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the manner of Bodies, nor in a Senſe agreeable to mortal Creatures: For this Conſtantiality, ſaid he, cannot be either by the Diviſion of Subſtance, or Abſciſſion or Change of the paternal Eſſence and Power: For all theſe things are inconſiſtent
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59696:38"/>with the uncreated Nature of the Father. But this Propoſition, To be of the ſame Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance with the Father, ſignifies no more, than that the Son of God hath no Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity with, nor Reſemblance to created Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but that in every Reſpect he is like to the Father only, who hath begotten him; and that he does exiſt of no other Subſtance or Eſſence, but of the Father.</p>
            <p>To this Opinion thus explained, <hi>Euſebius</hi> gave his Aſſent: And he was the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinable to do this, becauſe that he knew ſome of the Ancient Learned and Eminent Biſhops and Writers had uſed the Term <hi>Homoouſios</hi> in their Explanations of the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the Father and of the Son.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Euſebius Pamphilus</hi> having ſaid thus much concerning the Creed publiſhed at <hi>Nice,</hi> the Hiſtorian obſerves, that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops did not haſtily, but with deep Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration and mature Examining, agree unto it, and that every Man's Senſe was fairly diſcuſs'd before the Emperour, and that their Conſents to what was concluded, was free and unanimous. As to the Anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm publiſhed by the Fathers after the Creed, the ſame was lik'd by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> in regard it did prohibit the Uſe of Terms that occur not in the Scriptures. From the uſe of which Terms came almoſt all the Confuſion and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59696:38"/>Diſturbance that had been raiſed in the Church: And ſince no Part of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, given by Divine Inſpiration has made uſe of theſe <hi>Arian</hi> Terms, <hi>viz.</hi> of Things which exiſt not: And there was a time when he was not: It was concluded as a thing agreeable to Reaſon, that theſe things ſhould neither be mentioned nor taught; which <hi>Euſebius</hi> calls a good and ſound Determination; and ſaith, that in former Times no ſuch Expreſſions were made uſe of; ſo that they were the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of the Heretick <hi>Arius,</hi> and firſt uſed by him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> having given the People of his Dioceſs this Account of his Backwardneſs in conſenting to the Creed drawn up, and formed by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, and of his final Agreement with them; All things were happily concluded, and the Holy Synod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed to ſend an Epiſtle to the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and to the Inhabitants of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt, Libya</hi> and <hi>Pentapolis,</hi> and therein to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint them with the Matters determined by the Synod; and how they had degra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Arius,</hi> and all thoſe who embraced his Opinion. A Copy of which Letter is, as now follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:59696:39"/>
                  <head>The Synodical Epiſtle.</head>
                  <head>To the Holy and great Church of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandrians,</hi> and to our Beloved Brethren the Inhabitants of <hi>Aegypt, Libya</hi> and <hi>Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tapolis;</hi> the Biſhops aſſembled at <hi>Nice,</hi> who fill up that Great and Holy <hi>Synod,</hi> ſend Greeting in the Lord.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FOraſmuch as by the Grace of God and (the Summons) of the pious Emperour</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine <hi>(who has call'd us together out of divers Cities and Provinces,) a Great and Holy Synod has been conven'd at</hi> Nice, <hi>it ſeem'd altogether neceſſary, that a Letter ſhould be written unto you in the Name of the</hi> Sacred Synod, <hi>whereby you might underſtand what things were there pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and what taken into Examination, as alſo what were decreed and eſtabliſh'd.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt of all therefore, the Impiety and Iniquity of</hi> Arius <hi>and his Complices, was enquir'd into, in the Preſence of the moſt pious Emperour</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine, <hi>and the Council's Determination (which was confirm'd by the Suffrages of all) was, that his impious Opinion and execrable Terms and Names, ſhould be anathematiz'd, which he blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly uſed, affirming that the Son of God had his Being of Nothing, and that there was a time when he was not; as alſo ſaying that the Son of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59696:39"/>God had a Freedom of Will, whereby he was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of Vertue or Vice; and calls him a Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and a Work. All theſe</hi> Tenets <hi>the</hi> Holy Synod <hi>hath anathematiz'd, not enduring ſo much as patiently to hear this impious Opinion, or rather Madneſs, and theſe blaſphemous Expreſſions.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But what Iſſue theſe Proceedings againſt them are arriv'd at, you have either heard already, or will hear; leſt we ſhould inſult over a Man who hath receiv'd a condign Recompence for his own Wickedneſs. But his Impiety was grown ſo prevalent, that he drew into the ſame Pit of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition,</hi> Theonas, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Marmarica, <hi>and</hi> Secundus, <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Ptolemais: <hi>For the ſame Sentence that had been given againſt him, was pronounc'd againſt them.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Thus far the Synodical Letter reſpects the Synod's Proceeding againſt <hi>Arius:</hi> The Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of the Letter concerns <hi>Melitus,</hi> and thoſe that by him had been admitted into Holy Orders. It pleaſed the Synod to uſe Gentleneſs toward <hi>Melitus,</hi> and not to treat him according to the ſtricteſt Senſe and Rigour of the Law: For they ſuffered him to continue in the City, but to have no Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, nor to ordain nor to propoſe the Names of thoſe that were to be ordained, or to appear in any Village or City upon this Pretence; but that he ſhould barely enjoy
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59696:40"/>his Appellation and Title. But to return to the Synodical Epiſtle: Wherein it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appears, that the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers did not only anathematize <hi>Arius</hi> and his Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, but alſo the very Terms of his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion. They alſo condemned his Book entitled <hi>Thalia,</hi> which he writ in Defence of his Hereſie. The Doctrine contain'd in that Book, was looſe and diſſolute, much reſembling (ſaith <hi>Socrates Scholaſticus</hi>) the Songs and Verſes of <hi>Sotades,</hi> the <hi>Maronite,</hi> an obſcene <hi>Greek</hi> Poet. This <hi>Thalia</hi> written by <hi>Arius, Athanaſius</hi> takes Notice of in his Second Oration againſt the <hi>Arians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was the Synod only ſollicitous about writing Letters concerning the Peace reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Church, but alſo the Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> ſignified the ſame, as appears by his Epiſtles extant in <hi>Socrates,</hi> one of which was written to the People of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and is as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Conſtantinus Auguſtus <hi>to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church of</hi> Alexander.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GOd ſave you (Beloved Brethren.) We have received this great Bleſſing from the Divine Providence, that being releas'd from all Errour, we now embrace and profeſs one and the ſame Faith. The Devil hath no longer Dominion over
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59696:40"/>us: For all the Machinations he deſign'd againſt us, are now totally deſtroyed: The bright Luſtre of Truth has defeated and expell'd all Diſſentions, Schiſms, Tumults, and (if I may ſo term them) all fatal Poyſons of Diſcord. We all adore one God in Name; and we believe that he is: And that this might be effected by the Wiſdom and Goodneſs of God, we conven'd a great Number of Biſhops at the City of</hi> Nice, <hi>and we our ſelf made one of the Number; and it is our ſingular Joy, that we are your Fellow-Servant, and have undertook the Diſquiſition of the Truth. We did therefore enquire into, and accurately diſcuſs all things which ſeem'd to yield the leaſt Occaſion of Ambiguity or Diſſention. But how great and horrid were the Blaſphemies concerning our great Saviour, concerning our Hope and Life? How have ſome openly ſpoken and profeſs'd that they believe things which are contrary to the Divinely inſpired Scriptures, and to the ſacred Faith?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>After that, no fewer than three hundred Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and upwards, admirable both for Moderation and Acuteneſs of Underſtanding, have unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly confirmed one and the ſame Faith (which according to the Verity and accurate Diſquiſition of the Divine Law, can only be the Faith)</hi> Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us <hi>poſſeſs'd with a Diabolical Spirit, was found to be the only Perſon, who with an impious Mind diſſeminated this Miſchief firſt amongſt you, and afterwards amongſt others. Let us embrace that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:59696:41"/>Opinion which God has delivered: Let us return to our beloved Brethren, from whom this impudent Servant of the Devil has ſeparated us: Let us with Diligence haſten to the common Body, and to our own genuine Members. For it becomes our Prudence, Faith and Sanctity, that ſince his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, (who hath been evidently prov'd to be an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of the Truth) is confuted, we ſhould return to the Divine Grace. For that which was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved of by three hundred Biſhops, can be judged nothing elſe but the Determination of God. For doubtleſs the Holy Ghoſt reſiding in the Minds of ſuch great and worthy Perſons hath diſcloſed to them the Will of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherefore let none of you continue dubious, let none of you make Delays: But you all with great Chearfulneſs return to the right Way, that when we come unto you (which ſhall be as ſoon as poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) we may together with you, return due Thanks to God (who inſpects all things) becauſe he has revealed the pure Faith, and thereby reſtored to you that mutual Love, which was the ſubject of good Mens Prayers. My beloved Brethren, God preſerve you.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Thus wrote the Emperour to the People of <hi>Alexandria:</hi> And from his affectionate Letter we may conclude, That the Deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Faith was not made unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly and in Haſte; but with a mature
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59696:41"/>Diſquiſition and diligent Examination of the Matters in Controverſie, every thing being exactly poiz'd and conſider'd by the Council, and nothing paſs'd by in Silence that was fit to be ſpoken of, every Man having Liberty to produce and urge what he was able in Behalf of his Opinion: So that the Controverſie was not inconſiderate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determined, but with great Accuracy firſt diſcuſs'd: Inſomuch that all things whatſoever which ſeem'd to produce Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Ambiguity or Diſſention, were wholly cleared and removed. And things being ſo prudently and piouſly manag'd and the Diſputes carried on with that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Calmneſs and Temper, the Emperour thought the Determination of all thoſe there aſſembled, could be nothing elſe but the <hi>Will of God,</hi> and he ſtuck not to affirm, That the Unanimity of ſo many and ſuch eminent Prelates, was procur'd by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But the Conduct of the Synod, tho' it was even prudent to a Wonder; yet there were thoſe who thought it to be orberwiſe, and who reflected upon the <hi>Nicene</hi> Biſhops as ſo many Idiots and ignorant Fellows; of which Number was <hi>Sabinus,</hi> the Ring-lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Hereſie. This Man was not aſhamed to aſperſe even <hi>Euſebius
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59696:42"/>Caeſarienſis</hi> with the Imputation of Ignorance, and to accuſe the whole Synod of Raſhneſs and Indiſcretion; not conſidering that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tho' the Fathers in that Synod had been I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diots, yet in regard they were illuminated by God, and directed by the Holy Ghoſt, they cou'd in no wiſe err from the Truth.</p>
            <p>The Emperour having writ in particular to the <hi>Alexandrians,</hi> he ſent another Lettter to the Biſhops and People of other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, wherein he ſets down what had been decreed againſt <hi>Arius</hi> and thoſe who em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brac'd his Opinion; and that ſeeing he had followed the Practices of wicked and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane Perſons, it was but juſt that he ſhou'd undergo the ſame ignominy with them: And that as <hi>Porphyrus,</hi> an Enemy of true Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, found a juſt Recompence for compoſing impious Volumes againſt Religion, and ſuch a Recompence as had rendred him ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious to Poſterity, and cover'd him with Infamy and Reproach: So it ſeemed reaſonable to term <hi>Arius</hi> and thoſe of his Opinion, <hi>Porphyrians,</hi> and that they ſhould derive a Name from him whom they ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly imitated: And the Emperour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands that if any Book could be met with that was writ by <hi>Arius,</hi> it ſhould be imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately burnt: That by this Means not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his wicked Doctrine might be wholly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59696:42"/>but alſo that not one Monument of him ſhould be left to Poſterity: And the Emperour in the ſame Letter further decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that if any Perſon ſhould be found to conceal any Book compil'd by <hi>Arius,</hi> and did not immediately produce and burn it, he ſhould ſuffer Death immediately upon his being found guilty.</p>
            <p>To this Letter of the Emperour, <hi>Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> alludes in his Epiſtle <hi>ad Solitar.</hi> and blames him for endeavouring to admit the <hi>Arians</hi> into the Church, ſeeing that he himſelf had fixt upon them the ignominious and execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Name of <hi>Porphyrians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is evident this Letter did not concern the Council of <hi>Nice:</hi> For it makes not any Mention of it: But it did proceed from the Emperour's pious Zeal to have the Heretick <hi>Arius</hi> utterly ſuppreſs'd; againſt whom and the Followers of his Opinion, he wrote ſeveral other Letters, which he caus'd to be publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in every City, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, which was to propoſe to publick View thoſe Reſcripts they wrote to the Cities: And at the Cloſe of every Reſcript they added this Word <hi>[Proponatur] let it be publiſhed.</hi> So <hi>Conſtantine</hi> when he wrote many Letters againſt <hi>Arius</hi> and his Followers, commanded they ſhould be propounded to publick View in the <hi>Forum.</hi>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:59696:43"/>And in all his Letters againſt <hi>Arius,</hi> he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents him as an infamous Perſon, and rebukes him with great Warmth and Sharpneſs.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Arius</hi> his Opinion, and all Books and Perſons favouring it, being cenſur'd and anathematiz'd; Two of his moſt eminent Abettors, namely <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis,</hi> began to retract what they had done; upon which they ſent a Libel of Repentance to the moſt conſiderable Biſhops, declaring their Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Expoſition of the Faith given by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers. Hereupon they were by Imperial Order recall'd from Exile, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admitted to their Sees. This happen'd in the third Year after the Synod, that is, in the 328th Year of Chriſt. Upon their Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, thoſe who had been ordain'd in their Places were removed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> put out <hi>Amphion,</hi> and <hi>Theognis, Creſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Libel containing the Recantation of <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis,</hi> being very remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, I thought it very proper here to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert it.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:59696:43"/>
                  <head>The Libel of Recantation made by <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Theognis,</hi> two notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Sticklers for <hi>Arius.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE having ſometime ſince been condemned by your Piety, without having our Cauſe declar'd or defended, ought quietly to bear what has been determin'd by your holy Diſcretion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But becauſe it is abſurd, by ſilence to give Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of Calumny againſt our ſelves, for this we declare to you, that we have unanimouſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed to the Determination about the Faith: And alſo, after we had made Reſearches into the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of</hi> Homoouſios, <hi>with our utmoſt Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, labour'd for Peace, having never been Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of any Hereſie: And when we had ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted whatever came into our Minds upon the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the Churches Security, and had fully ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied thoſe that ought to be perſuaded by us, we ſubſcrib'd the Faith, but have not ſubſcrib'd the Anathematiſm. Not that we had any thing to object againſt the Faith, but becauſe we did not believe the Perſon accuſed to be ſuch a one, as he was repreſented; having been fully ſatisfied that he was no ſuch Perſon; partly by the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Letters that he wrote us, and partly by the Diſcourſe that he made in our Preſence: But if your Holy Council was then ſatisfied, we now make no Reſiſtance, but agree to what you have
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59696:44"/>determined. And by this Libel we do fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and confirm our Conſent, which we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd to do, not becauſe we look upon our Exile to be tedious and burthenſome, but that we might avoid the Suſpicion of Hereſie: For if you ſhall now vouchſafe to let us return to your Preſence, you ſhall find us to be of the ſame Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with you in all Points, and quietly adhere to what you have determin'd: And ſince it hath ſeem'd to your Piety, to treat with great Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs even</hi> Arius, <hi>who is accus'd for theſe things, and to recall him from Baniſhment: Seeing that he who ſeem'd guilty, is recall'd, and has made his Defence in Reference to thoſe things laid to his Charge; upon this Conſideration it may juſtly ſeem abſurd, that we ſhould be ſilent, and by that Means yield an Argument againſt our ſelves. Do you therefore as befits the Piety of ſuch as love Chriſt. Remind the Emperour of us, and to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer up our Supplications to him, and ſpeedily to determine concerning us as ſhall be moſt agreeable to your Prudence.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>By this Libel it appears, that <hi>Euſebius</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> and <hi>Theognis</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Nice,</hi> did ſubſcribe the Faith which had been publiſhed, but wou'd not give their Conſent to the depoſing of <hi>Arius.</hi> It like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe appears by the ſame Libel, that <hi>Arius</hi> was recall'd from Baniſhment before the
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59696:44"/>two Biſhops; which was done by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and not the Fathers. But tho' he was recall'd, yet he was forbid to enter <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria:</hi> And this <hi>Socrates</hi> concludes from the Way he afterwards invented for his own Return into that Church and City; which was (ſaith <hi>Socrates</hi>) his making uſe of a counterfeit Repentance.</p>
            <p>'Tis certain <hi>Euſebius</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> and his Confederates made it their Buſineſs to bring <hi>Arius</hi> back again to <hi>Alexandria.</hi> But how they prevail'd in their Deſign, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what Manner the Emperour was wrought upon to admit <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Euzoius</hi> into his Preſence, comes now to be ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinctly reported.</p>
            <p>The Emperour <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had a Siſter call'd <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> who had been married to <hi>Licinius,</hi> once Collegue with him in the Empire. This <hi>Conſtantia</hi> had a Prieſt for her Confident, who was reckon'd among her Domeſticks, and a great Favourer of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rianiſm.</hi> This Man, prompted thereunto by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and thoſe of his Faction, did in his familiar Diſcourſe with <hi>Conſtantia</hi> let fall ſome Words concerning <hi>Arius,</hi> ſaying, That the Synod had done him Wrong, and that his Sentiments were not as they repreſented. <hi>Conſtantia</hi> was eaſily induc'd to believe what was told her by the Presbyter: But ſhe
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59696:45"/>wanted Confidence to declare it to the Emperour. It happen'd that <hi>Conſtantia</hi> fell dangerouſly ſick, and was daily viſited by the Emperour; and finding her Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to grow mortal, and expecting nothing but immediate Death, ſhe recommended the Presbyter to his Royal Favour, praiſing his Diligence and Piety, aſſuring the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of his good Affection to his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. <hi>Conſtantia</hi> dying, her Brother made the ſame Presbyter one of his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Confidents, who having by Degrees got a Liberty of ſpeaking to the Emperour, took his Opportunity to tell him many things concerning <hi>Arius,</hi> affirming, he had no other Sentiments, than what were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Synod's Determination; and that if the Emperour would admit him to his Preſence, he would give Conſent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what the Synod had decreed. He told him alſo that <hi>Arius</hi> without all Reaſon had been falſly accus'd.</p>
            <p>The Emperour ſeem'd much ſurpriz'd with what the Presbyter told him, and ſaid, that if <hi>Arius</hi> would conſent to the Synod's Determination, and declare that he was of the ſame Judgment with the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, he would admit him to his Preſence, and alſo ſend him back to <hi>Alexandria</hi> with Repute and Honour.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59696:45"/>And the Emperour having ſaid thus, he immediately wrote to <hi>Arius</hi> after this Manner.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Victor Conſtantinus Maximus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus <hi>to</hi> Arius.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>IT has ſometime ſince been made known to your Gravity, that you ſhould repair to our Court, in order to your being admitted to the Enjoyment of our Preſence: And we much admire that you have not forthwith perform'd this. Wherefore immediately take a publick Chariot, and come with ſpeed to our Court, that having experienc'd our Care and good Will, you may return to your own Country. God preſerve you, Beloved Brother. Dated before the firſt of the Calends of</hi> December.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Arius</hi> upon receiving this Letter, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly repair'd to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with <hi>Euzoius,</hi> whom <hi>Alexander</hi> had diveſted of his Deaconſhip, when he depos'd <hi>Arius</hi> and his Aſſociates. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour admits them both into his Preſence, and ask'd them whether they would agree to the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith; and they readily giving their Aſſent, the Emperour commanded them to deliver in a Libel containing their Faith. Whereupon they drew up a Libel
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:59696:46"/>of Repentance, which they preſented to the Emperour, and was as follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>Arius <hi>and</hi> Euzoius <hi>to our moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and moſt Pious Lord</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine <hi>the Emperour.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ACcording to the Order of your Piety (moſt acceptable to God, our Lord the Emperour) we declare our Faith, and in Writing profeſs in the Preſence of God, that we, and all our Adherents do believe, as follows:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>WE believe in one God, the Father Almighty; and in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, who was made before all VVorlds; God the VVord, by whom all things were made that are in Heaven and that are in Earth: VVho came down from Heaven, and was incarnate, and ſuffered and roſe again, and aſcended into the Heavens: who alſo ſhall come again to judge the Quick and the Dead. VVe alſo believe in the Holy Ghoſt, and in the Reſurrection of the Fleſh, and in the Life of the VVorld to come, and in the Kingdom of Heaven, and one Catholick Church of God, which is ſpread from one God of the VVorld to the other.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:59696:46"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>This Faith we have received from the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Goſpels, the Lord ſaying to his Diſciples,</hi> Go ye, and teach all Nations, baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>If we do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve theſe things, and if we do not admit of the Father, the Son and the Holy Ghoſt in ſuch Manner as the Holy Catholick Church and the Scriptures (which we believe in all things) do teach, God is our Judge both now and in the Judgment to come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>We therefore beſeech your Piety (O Emperour moſt acceptable to God) That being Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, and holding the Faith and Senſe of the Church and the Holy Scriptures, we may by your peaceful and religious Piety be united to the Church: All Queſtions and ſuperfluous Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions being wholly taken away and ſuppreſs'd; that ſo both we and the Church enjoying a mutual Peace and Union, may joyntly offer up our uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Prayers for the peaceable Reign of your impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty, and for your whole Family.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Arius</hi> having deluded the Emperour with this Libel of Repentance, obtain'd Leave to return to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where <hi>Athanaſius</hi> being made Biſhop upon the Death of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander,</hi> denied him Reception; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Arius</hi> attempted to ſtir up new Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions by diſperſing his Hereſie. And
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59696:47"/>albeit that both the Emperour and <hi>Euſebius</hi> wrote to <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> That <hi>Arius</hi> and his Complices might be admitted into the Church, yet <hi>Athanaſius</hi> utterly refuſed to grant them Admiſſion; acquainting the Emperour, that it was impoſſible for thoſe who once had rejected the Faith, and were anathematiz'd, to be entirely readmitted to their Degrees in the Church at their Return: For he held that the Ring-lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Hereſies are not ſo eaſily to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concil'd to the Church, as their deluded Followers; and that the Church had been always wont to puniſh them with greater and longer Severities. Beſides, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd that he was not at all ſatisfied con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sincerity of <hi>Arius</hi>'s Repentance; and therefore till further Trial was had of him, he would not hear of his Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution.</p>
            <p>This was preſently ſeiz'd upon by <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius Nicomedienſis</hi> as a fit Handle for his Deſign, who immediately goes to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, and informs him of <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s Carriage, complaining that he kept up Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord in the Church meerly to gratifie his private Piques and Animoſities: And, that contrary to his Duty and the Laws of the Church, he deny'd <hi>Arius</hi> Abſolution, when he deſir'd it upon his Repentance. The
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59696:47"/>Emperour hearing this, was highly incens'd, and being inſtigated by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> he wrote a threatning Letter to <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> Part of which was thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HAving receiv'd the Knowledge of our Wills do you grant a free Admiſſion and Entrance into the Church to all ſuch as deſire it: For if we receive Information that you have prohibited any of thoſe that are deſirous to be united to the Church, or have hindred their Admiſſion, we will im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſend one who ſhall be empower'd by our Order to depoſe you, and baniſh you your Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this ſharp Letter, <hi>Athanaſius</hi> returned ſuch a ſoft ſatisfactory Anſwer, as made the Emperour deſiſt from interpoſing any further in the Buſineſs: But <hi>Euſebius</hi> find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf defeated in this his Stratagem againſt <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> tampers with the <hi>Mele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Schiſmaticks of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to form a Plot againſt him. But this with all other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinations, were by the Divine Providence wonderfully diſappointed, as appears by the Hiſtory of thoſe Times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arius</hi> and his Followers were no ſooner return'd to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> but there began new Diſturbances.</p>
            <pb n="86" facs="tcp:59696:48"/>
            <p> The People of that City were much troubled at the Return of them, and at the Exile of <hi>Athanaſius.</hi> But the Emperour perceiving the perverſe and turbulent Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Arius,</hi> he orderd him to be ſent for again to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to give an Account of the Troubles he had laboured to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander,</hi> who ſometime before this had ſucceeded <hi>Metrophanes,</hi> did now preſide over the Church at <hi>Alexandria.</hi> This Man gave ſufficient Proof of his Piety and Accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs unto God, in the Conflict he at this Time had with <hi>Arius.</hi> Upon whoſe Arrival at that City the People divided in Factions, which caus'd an univerſal Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion amongſt them; ſome of them af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed ought to continue inviolate, and without any Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration; and others pertinaciouſly aſſerted that <hi>Arius</hi>'s Opinion was conſonant to Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. <hi>Alexander</hi> thereupon was reduced to a great Streight, and the more becauſe <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius Nicomedienſis</hi> had ſorely threatned him, ſaying, that he would forthwith cauſe him to be depoſed, unleſs he would admit <hi>Arius</hi> and his Followers into Communion: But <hi>Alexander</hi> was not ſo ſollicitous about his own Depoſition, as he was fearful of weakening the Faith, which the Heretick
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59696:48"/>and his Aſſociates, endeavoured to ſubvert: For looking upon himſelf as Guardian and Patron of the Determinations made by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Synod, he made it his Buſineſs to prevent the Wreſting and depraving of 'em. Being therefore reduc'd to ſignal Extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, he entirely bad farewel to all Humane Aſſiſtances, and humbly and ſolely depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon God; whom having made his only Refuge, he devoted himſelf continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to Faſting and Prayer: And having ſhut up himſelf in the Church <hi>Irene,</hi> he went to the Altar, and laying himſelf proſtrate on the Ground under the Holy Table; where for many Nights and Days together he poured forth his Prayers and Tears, begging of God, that if the Opinion of <hi>Arius</hi> was true, he might not live to ſee the Day ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to diſcuſs it: But if that which he profeſs'd was true, that <hi>Arius</hi> might receive ſome viſible condign Puniſhment for his Impiety in oppoſing it. And God was pleaſed to hear his Prayer: For the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour (ſaith the Hiſtory) being deſirous to make trial of <hi>Arius,</hi> ſends for him to the Palace, and ask'd him, whether he would give his Aſſent to the <hi>Nicene</hi> Determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: He without any Heſitation ſaid he would, and ſubſcrib'd them in the Preſence of the Emperour, who admiring at it, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:59696:49"/>him to ſwear to the Truth of what he had ſubſcrib'd; which he alſo did, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſe of Artifice and Fraud; which was thus. <hi>Arius</hi> having writ down his Opinion in Paper, hid it under his Arm-pit, and ſwore that he really thought as he had written.</p>
            <p>That <hi>Arius</hi> did both ſwear and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe to the Determinations of the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Synod, appears by the Emperour's own Letters; but for the Deceit he uſed in ſwearing, Hiſtorians are not poſitive.</p>
            <p>But the Emperour believing that <hi>Arius</hi> dealt ſincerely in what he ſwore and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd, preſently gave Order to <hi>Alexander,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> to admit him to Communion. It was then <hi>Saturday;</hi> and on the next Day he expected to be a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Aſſembly of Believers: But Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Vengeance follow'd him ſo cloſely that he did not live till next Day: For when he came out of the Imperial Palace attended by the <hi>Euſebian</hi> Party, like Guards, through the midſt of the City, the Eyes of all People being upon him, as he came near the Place call'd <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s <hi>Forum,</hi> he was ſeiz'd with a horrible Terror, proceeding from his Guilt, which was accompanied with a Looſneſs. Hereupon he enquired for a Houſe of Office, and underſtanding there was one behind <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s <hi>Forum,</hi> he
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59696:49"/>went thither; whither he was no ſooner come, but he was ſeiz'd with a fainting Fit, and together with his Excrements his Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dament fell down, and a great Flux of Blood, his Spleen, Liver and Small Guts all guſh'd out together: So that he immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately expir'd.</p>
            <p>The Suddenneſs and Manner of <hi>Arius</hi>'s Death occaſion'd a great Fear and Anxiety amongſt thoſe of the Faction; and it mov'd the Emperour to ſay, that God himſelf had confirm'd the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith. But con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to all Expectation, the Hereſie ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viv'd the Heretick, it being kept alive by <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius:</hi> Who tho' he had no great Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> yet he could not endure the Word <hi>Homoouſios,</hi> nor thoſe who defend-it. And it is very obſervable, that after the <hi>Nicene</hi> Council, the <hi>Euſebians</hi> never appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bare-fac'd in the Behalf of the <hi>Arian</hi> Doctrine, and yet they were ſtill angry with the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, meerly for the ſake of the Term <hi>Homoouſios. Euſebius</hi> by the Intereſt he had got in <hi>Conſtantine</hi>'s Court, had great Opportunity of doing much Miſchief to the Church: And where his Malice and Revenge were concern'd, he was never wanting to do his worſt. It appears by what is related of his Carriage, that he was a proud Man, of an implacable
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59696:50"/>Spirit, and one who could not brook any thing that he apprehended to be an Injury or an Affront: which unhappy Temper put him upon ſtudying nothing ſo much as Revenge. And <hi>Athanaſius</hi> appear'd on all Occaſions to be the main and peculiar Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of his Malice. For he could never forget how that excellent Perſon had born down him and his whole Party, in the Synod of <hi>Nice.</hi> Now for ſo powerful a Prelate as <hi>Euſebius,</hi> to be top'd by ſo mean a Perſon as <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> who had attain'd no higher Degree in the Church than that of a Deacon: For <hi>Euſebius,</hi> I ſay, by ſo mean a Perſon to be brought on his Knees and forc'd to publick Submiſſion, was an Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity ſo intolerable to the proud Spirit of <hi>Euſebius,</hi> that neither the Blood of <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius,</hi> nor of all his Friends was ſufficient to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate his unquenchable Revenge: And all the Accuſations forg'd againſt <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> were of ſuch Crimes, for which nothing leſs than capital Puniſhments could be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted. For they laid to his Charge no Sin inferiour to Murther, Rapes and Treaſon; as is to be ſeen in <hi>Athanaſius</hi>'s ſecond Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy.</p>
            <p>Another Pique <hi>Euſebius</hi> had againſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> was his not reſtoring <hi>Arius</hi> at his Requeſt. And, as <hi>Socrates</hi> informs us,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59696:50"/>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſet all his Wit at Work to undo <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and to root out the Doctrine of Conſubſtantiality, and that for no other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but becauſe he was not the Author of it himſelf; and that it was brought into the Creed by <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> and others whom he hated. But not only <hi>Euſebius,</hi> but alſo ſeveral others, either by his Example or by his Inſtigation, had their Minds much diſturbed about the ſame Point. And it appears (ſaith <hi>Socrates</hi>) by ſeveral Letters which the Biſhops wrote to one another af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Synod of <hi>Nice,</hi> that they were not all well pleas'd with the Term <hi>Homoouſios;</hi> which prov'd of ill Conſequence: For whilſt they were buſie about this Word, making but too curious Enquiries into its Importance and Meaning, they rais'd an inteſtine War amongſt themſelves: And what was done herein was not unlike a Fight in the Dark: For neither Side ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſee perfectly what they fell out about, or why they reviled one another. They that had an Averſion for the Term <hi>Homoou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſios,</hi> look'd upon them that embrac'd it, as Introducers of <hi>Sabellianiſm</hi> and of the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Followers of <hi>Montanus;</hi> who denied the three Perſons of the Godhead, ſaying, that the Father, Son and Holy Ghoſt are one and the ſame Perſon.</p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:59696:51"/>
            <p> On the other hand, they that were for the Word <hi>Homoouſios,</hi> abominated thoſe that were againſt it, looking upon them as bringers in of Polytheiſm: And tho' both ſides aſſerted that the Son of God had a proper, real and peculiar Perſon and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence; yet (how it came to paſs I know not) they could in no wiſe agree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, nor endure to be quiet. But the Biſhops wrote one againſt another with as much Bitterneſs as if they had been utter Enemies.</p>
            <p>But the Controverſie being long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued between the <hi>Euſebians</hi> and the Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith, the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie as if it had taken the Opportunity of this Contraſt, began again to appear upon the Stage, with a little Alteration in the Dreſs. For <hi>Photinus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Sirmium</hi> in <hi>Illyricum,</hi> reviv'd the old exploded Opinion of <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Samoſata,</hi> which differ'd from <hi>Arianiſm</hi> but in this one Circumſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> That it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms the Son of God was created, but not before his Nativity: Whereas <hi>Arius</hi> will have him to have been created the firſt of the Creatures. So that they differ only as to the time of his being created, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing in the Poyſon of the Hereſie: Namely, that Chriſt was created. But yet <hi>Arius</hi> was not altogether ſo degrading of
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59696:51"/>the <hi>Meſſias</hi> as <hi>Photinus:</hi> The Former allow'd him a great Share in the Creation of the Univerſe, and an Eminency, Power and Dignity over all other Creatures: But the Latter brought Chriſt down into the ſame Rank with every ordinary Man. This bold Hereſie alarm'd both the Catholicks and <hi>Euſebians,</hi> and both agree to have a Council call'd at <hi>Sirmium</hi> about it; where the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops being aſſembled, they condemn'd the <hi>Photinian</hi> Hereſie, and compos'd a large Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Faith, which they ſent to the Biſhops of <hi>Italy.</hi> In which Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they take Notice that <hi>Photinus</hi> and his Followers deriv'd their Hereſie from the <hi>Jews,</hi> who deny the eternal Exiſtence and Godhead of Chriſt, holding that the <hi>Meſſias</hi> whom they ſtill expect ſhall be by Nature a meer Man, and be Deified only by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion: Which <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Blaſphemy being defended by <hi>Photinus,</hi> he was juſtly depos'd by a Synod of Biſhops, which the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour conven'd at <hi>Sirmium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding that he was Syno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically depoſed, yet the Sentence of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition was not irrevocable: For we find that <hi>Photinus</hi> might have been reſtor'd to his Biſhoprick, if he would have alter'd his Mind, and anathematiz'd his Opinion, and conſented to the Sentiments of the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59696:52"/>Council. But he was ſo far from doing this, that he challeng'd the Biſhops to a Diſpute, and to vindicate what he held. <hi>Baſilius</hi> at that time preſiding over the Church of <hi>Ancyra,</hi> accepted the Challenge, and enter'd Diſputation with <hi>Photinus,</hi> and an Account of their Diſpute was taken by Notaries appointed for that Purpoſe. The Combat was on both ſides manag'd with Warmth. <hi>Photinus</hi> in the End was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, and condemn'd to Exile; in which he ſpent the Reſidue of his Life in writing againſt Hereſies.</p>
            <p>But the Miſchief ended not in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Baniſhment of <hi>Photinus:</hi> For at <hi>Antioch</hi> in <hi>Syria</hi> there aroſe another Arch-Heretick, one <hi>Aetius,</hi> Sirnamed <hi>Atheus.</hi> He was of the ſame Opinion with <hi>Arius,</hi> but yet ſeparated from the <hi>Arians;</hi> becauſe they had admitted <hi>Arius</hi> into Communion, whom he deteſted for his Diſſimulation in holding one Opinion in his Mind and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Profeſſion of the contrary with his Mouth; as all knew he did in his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription (made before the Emperour) to the Form of the Creed drawn up by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers: For tho' <hi>Aetius</hi> was a zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Aſſertor of the <hi>Arian</hi> Doctrine, yet he would not joyn in Communion with thoſe who profeſs'd it: Becauſe when they knew
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59696:52"/>the Hypocriſie of <hi>Arius,</hi> they admitted him into their Fellowſhip. This <hi>Aetius,</hi> by what we find recorded of him, appears to have been a Man of little Learning, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilful in the Scriptures, and of a wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful contentious and diſputing Humour. He was not at all ſtudious in the Peruſal of thoſe ancient Writers, who had explain'd the ſacred Books of the Chriſtian Religion. And tho' he was of the ſame Opinion with the <hi>Arians,</hi> yet he was ſo obſtruſe in his Arguments for it, and his Sentiments were ſo perplex'd, that the <hi>Arians</hi> themſelves not being able to underſtand 'em, judg'd him to be an Heretick: And as ſuch he was driven from their Communion.</p>
            <p>But to conclude all I have to ſay at preſent on this Subject: There happen'd at laſt ſuch an happy Agreement amongſt the Biſhops, as thro' the Bleſſing of God turn'd to the caſting out of that evil Spirit of <hi>Arianiſm,</hi> which had ſo long tormented the Church. For the Biſhops being by the Death of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantius</hi> freed from that Violence and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion which that Emperour and his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, had put upon the Diſcipline of the Church; and being at Liberty to exert that Authority wherewith Chriſt himſelf had veſted them: They reſtor'd that Peace and Concord to the Church which they could
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59696:53"/>never compaſs under <hi>Conſtantius;</hi> and put an End to the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie, and eſtabliſh'd the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith over the Chriſtian World. Which wonderful Felicity was by God's Providence chiefly procur'd by the Zeal Piety and wiſe Conduct of <hi>Athanaſius;</hi> who being reſtored by the Synod of <hi>Sardica,</hi> returned to <hi>Alexandria:</hi> Where he preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly call'd a Council for the Reſettlement of the Catholick Church; which by the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and long Oppreſſion of <hi>Conſtantius</hi> had been miſerably haraſs'd and diſturb'd. The Biſhops being aſſembled, they luckily hit upon ſeveral healing Concluſions. As</p>
            <p n="1">1. That thoſe Biſhops who had joyn'd with the Hereticks, either out of Ignorance, Surprize, or Violence, upon their Return to the Catholick Church, ſhould be receiv'd without Deprivation of Dignity; becauſe their Compliance with the <hi>Arians</hi> was to be look'd upon as Want of Prudence, and not as an Apoſtacy from the Orthodox Faith. For tho' for Peace ſake ſome of the Biſhops that were reſtor'd, had conſented to have the Word <hi>Hoomouſios,</hi> or Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial left out of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed, yet they a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathematiz'd all the Points of the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie, and ſhew'd that they were not tainted therewith. But as to thoſe Biſhops
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59696:53"/>who had been the Ring-leaders of Hereſie, they were ſo depriv'd as never to riſe Lay-Communion. Which was agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the ſtanding Diſcipline of the Church.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Synod adjuſted the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie which had lately happen'd between the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latins,</hi> concerning the Words <hi>Hypoſtaſis</hi> and <hi>Perſona.</hi> For <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſis</hi> being the ſame with <hi>Ouſia</hi> (ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Subſtance) the <hi>Latins</hi> thought that the <hi>Greeks</hi> own'd three diſtinct Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces when they profeſs'd the Belief of three <hi>Hypoſtaſes.</hi> And the <hi>Greeks</hi> finding that the <hi>Latins</hi> rejected the Word <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſis,</hi> and in Lieu thereof uſed the Word <hi>Perſona,</hi> they thought that they aſſerted nothing real, but a meer relative Diſtinction. The word <hi>Perſona</hi> general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denoting not the Man himſelf, but his Office and Relation. And the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt about theſe Words ran ſo high, that it had like to have produc'd a Breach between the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches. Which being foreſeen by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,</hi> he prudently to accommodate the Diſpute, propounded to the Synod, That both Words ſhould indifferently be made uſe of in both Churches. And
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59696:54"/>the Propoſition being agreed unto by the Synod, all Suſpicion on both ſides was remov'd, the preſent Controverſie ſilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and ſo continues to this Day.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> finding that the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Faith, which the <hi>Euſebian</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had preſented in the Council of <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica</hi> was by ſome mightily cry'd up as if it had been approv'd of by that Council, the <hi>Alexandrian</hi> Fathers took Care to undeceive the People in this important Affair; which they did by proving that the <hi>Euſebian</hi> Confeſſion was utterly rejected by the Council of <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dica;</hi> and that that Synod refuſed to alter any thing of the <hi>Nicene</hi> Faith.</p>
            <p>And the Council having thus ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted all Matters, and finiſhed their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, they drew them up in a Circular Letter, which they ſent to the Biſhops of the CHRISTIAN WORLD.</p>
            <p>And, as <hi>Athanſius</hi> took much Pains for ſettling the Church in <hi>Africa,</hi> ſo <hi>Hilarius</hi> did the like to reſtore the Church in <hi>France.</hi> And in order to this, he got a Council to be call'd at <hi>Paris,</hi> wherein the Proceedings at <hi>Ariminum</hi> were condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and the ancient Liberties reſtored to the Church, which ſhe enjoyed till
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59696:54"/>they were invaded by <hi>Conſtantius.</hi> In this Council thoſe that had ſubſcribed the Creed of <hi>Ariminum,</hi> confeſs'd their Fault in leaving out the Word <hi>Ouſia</hi> (or Subſtance) frankly owning that they had been over-reacht; and they took the Sacrament that they meant no harm in what they did, and that they abhorr'd the Conſequence that all Men made out of it; and ſo begg'd Pardon for what through Ignorance and Surprize had been done by them. This Council was ſo unanimous in their Opinions, that there was but one Diſſenter, Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>Saturninus,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Arles;</hi> who for his diſagreeing from the Synod, was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by it.</p>
            <p>And thus by the pious and diſcreet Care of <hi>Athanaſius</hi> in the Eaſt, and of <hi>Hilary</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the Church was ſettled in Peace and Truth, and a good Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondence maintain'd betwixt the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riental and <hi>French</hi> Biſhops, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned no ſmall Regret to the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of Chriſtianity; eſpecially to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> the Emperour, who uſed all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable Artifice to root it out, and to replant Paganiſm in its Room.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:59696:55"/>
            <p> This Apoſtate now put off his <hi>Viſor</hi> of pretended Kindneſs to the Chriſtians: And this happy Settlement of the Church ſo heightend his Malice, that as both <hi>Sozomen</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> obſerved, he out-did all his Anceſtors in Fury and Rage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chriſtians; who likewiſe out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did all their Anceſtors in Patience and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Julian,</hi> famouſly known by the <hi>Stig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> of Apoſtate, being dead, <hi>Jovian</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in the Empire. He found the Affairs of the Chriſtians in a very unſedate Condition, partly by reaſon of the malicious Induſtry his Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour had uſed totally to ſuppreſs them; and partly by the Diviſions that were among the Chriſtians themſelves. The laſt Stratagem invented by <hi>Julian</hi> to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpate the Chriſtians, was the Law he made,
<q>That Chriſtians ſhould not be allow'd an Education in Humane Literature; leſt, ſaid he, when they have therewith ſharpen'd their Tongues, they ſhou'd with greater Readineſs anſwer the Heathen Diſputants.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Law occaſion'd the two <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linaris's,</hi> Father and Son to write with good Succeſs in Behalf of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians.
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59696:55"/>The one was famous for <hi>Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> and the other for <hi>Rhetorick.</hi> But Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions among the Chriſtians were moſt obſtructive of their Peace.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Jovian</hi>'s Entrance upon his Reign, the Principal Heads of every Party made their (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Addreſſes to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, in hopes they ſhou'd obtain from him Power and Authority againſt thoſe whom they reputed their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baſilius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ancyra,</hi> with ſix o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Biſhops, preſented a ſupplicatory Libel to the Emperour, in behalf of the <hi>Macedonians,</hi> who took their Name from <hi>Macedonius,</hi> an <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople.</hi> They held that Chriſt
<q>was not of the ſame Eſſence with the Father,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A. D.</hi> 343.</note> but only like unto him: And that the Holy Ghoſt was not God, but God's Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and no more eternal than any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creature.</q> Theſe Hereticks were never conſtant in their Doctrine; but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Arians,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Semi-Arians,</hi> and ſometimes <hi>Orthodox.</hi> In the Name of theſe Weather-Cock Hereticks, <hi>Baſilius</hi> and his Fellows ſupplicate the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, that all thoſe who Aſſerted the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59696:56"/>Son to be more than barely like the Father, might be caſt out of their Churches, and themſelves put in their Places.</p>
            <p>The Emperour having received their Addreſs, ſends them away without any other Anſwer,
<q>than that he abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Contentiouſneſs, and loved and honour'd thoſe who were deſirous of Unity and Concord.</q> Which Words had the good Effect to mollifie their Stiſſneſs, who were Lovers of Contention: Which was the Thing deſign'd and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Emperour.</p>
            <p>At this time alſo the <hi>Icacians</hi> (who held,
<q>That the Son was a Creature made by the Father, and like him in Will, but not in Subſtance) began to ſhew their Diſpoſition to Unpeaceable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</q> They were indeed Notorious Trimmers, and ever ready to be of their Judgment who were uppermoſt and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt to promote 'em.</p>
            <p>Theſe meeting with <hi>Meletius</hi> at <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,</hi> in <hi>Syria,</hi> and entring into Diſcourſe with him, and finding that he embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the <hi>Homoouſion</hi> Doctrine, and that he was highly in Favour with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, they made Profeſſion of the ſame
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59696:56"/>Doctrine and conform'd to the <hi>Nicene</hi> Greed. And by a general Conſent drew up a Libel and preſented it to <hi>Jovinian:</hi> which is to be ſeen in <hi>Socrates, Book 3. Chap.</hi> 25. <hi>Eccleſ. Hiſt.</hi> In which Libel they in particular declared their Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing the Term <hi>Homoouſias,</hi> as it was with great Caution explain'd by the <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cene</hi> Fathers: And at the ſame time publickly declared, firſt, That the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of the Son was inexplicable. 2. That the Term <hi>Ouſia</hi> was not taken by the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers in the uſual Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification which the <hi>Grecians</hi> put upon it; but that they made uſe of it in order to the Subverſion of what had been impiouſly and audaciouſly held by <hi>Arius</hi> concerning Chriſt, who affirmed, <hi>That he exiſted of things that were not.</hi> (Which Opinion the Upſtart <hi>Eunomeans</hi> maintain'd to the great Diſturbance of Eccleſiaſtick Unity.) 3. They aſſur'd the Emperour, that in all Points they did agree to the Belief ſet forth by the Biſhops convened at <hi>Nicaea.</hi> And the Biſhops, who conſented to the Libel, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed their Names.</p>
            <pb n="104" facs="tcp:59696:57"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Jovian</hi> graciouſly received the ſaid Libel, and ſeem'd not at all concerned what Opinion they were of, ſo long as they kept themſelves quiet. And it is very obſervable, That by kind Words and Perſuaſives he mightily ſuppreſs'd the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions Humour then on foot, and ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calm'd their Fury, who made it their Buſineſs to cavil and contend. And by his dextrous Management, if <hi>Jovian</hi> had liv'd, both the Civil and Eccleſiaſtick Aſſairs of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire might in all Probability, have been fortunate and ſuccesful. But alas! a ſudden Death de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd both Church and State of this excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſonage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Jovianus</hi> having ended his Life at <hi>Dadaſtana,</hi> on the Frontiers of <hi>Galatia</hi> and <hi>Bithynia,</hi> after the ſhort Reign of ſeven Months, <hi>Valentinianus,</hi> by an una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous Suffrage of the Soldiers, was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to ſucceed him. Upon which Choiſe, he ſtraightway made his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Valens</hi> his Collegue in the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. They were both Chriſtians; but both diſagreed about the Faith of the Chriſtian Religion. <hi>Valentinianus</hi> had a Veneration for the <hi>Nicene</hi> Creed. <hi>Valens</hi> by reaſon of a Prepoſſeſſion, adhered
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59696:57"/>to the <hi>Arian</hi> Hereſie. And this his Pre-poſſeſſion aroſe from his being bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized by <hi>Eudoxius</hi> of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of the <hi>Arian</hi> Opinion.</p>
            <p>Both the Brothers were very warm in Maintenance of the Sentiments to which they adhered: And though they agreed in the Care of the Civil Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, yet they differed much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Chriſtian Religion. And were very different in their Carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſuch as profeſs'd it. For <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinianus,</hi> though he much favoured thoſe who were of his Judgment, yet he was not in the leaſt troubleſome to the <hi>Arians.</hi> But <hi>Valens</hi> deſirous to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the <hi>Arians,</hi> did moſt grievouſly diſturb and moleſt thoſe who differed from them in Opinion. Every Sect had their Biſhops to preſide over them. And all but the Orthodox were ſtill ſtriving to mend the Belief of <hi>Nice:</hi> To which Purpoſe the <hi>Macedoniani</hi> deſire the Emperour <hi>Valens</hi> to give leave to convene a Synod.</p>
            <p>He ſuppoſing that they had been of the ſame Opinion with <hi>Acacius</hi> and <hi>Eudoxius,</hi> granted their Requeſt.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:59696:58"/>
            <p> Accordingly a Council met at <hi>Lamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacus,</hi> nigh the <hi>Helleſpont.</hi> It was a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod of <hi>Macedonian</hi> Hereticks, and it ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tify'd the Council which Seven Years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had been held at <hi>Seleucia, A. D.</hi> 363, and damned that of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> held by the <hi>Acacians.</hi> They alſo ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematiz'd the <hi>Creed,</hi> that was publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Arimine,</hi> though they had before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their Agreement in Opinion with thoſe that held it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Valens</hi> was much incenſed againſt this Synod, both becauſe it had depoſed the <hi>Arian</hi> Biſhops, and anathematized that Draught of the Creed, publiſhed at <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</hi> And the Emperour was reſolved to leave no Means unattempted where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he might win all Perſons to <hi>Aria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm. Eluſius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Cizicum,</hi> was the firſt he aggreſſed; who for fear of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Eſtate, turned <hi>Arian.</hi> And the very <hi>Semi-Arians</hi> fared no better than the <hi>Orthodox;</hi> but all were the Object of his perſecuting Spirit, who were not thoroughly <hi>Arianized.</hi> But his Rage was moſt viſibly exerciſed againſt the <hi>Homo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſians,</hi> whom he perſecuted in all thoſe who bore them any Eſteem or good Will. He was much ſtirred up to this Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59696:58"/>by the <hi>Arian</hi> Prelate <hi>Eudoxius,</hi> by whoſe Inſtigation he turned out the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox</hi> Clergy; who during the ſixteen Years that <hi>Valens</hi> reigned, ſcarce ever enjoyed the Comfort of one peaceable Day.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:59696:59"/>
            <head>Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>R. Clavel,</hi> at the <hi>Peacock</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard.</head>
            <p>THE Church Hiſtory cleared from the <hi>Roman</hi> Forgeries and Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons found in the Councils and <hi>Baronius:</hi> In Four Parts. From the Beginning of Chriſtianity, to the End of the fifth General Council. 553. By <hi>Thomas Comber, D.D. Dean of</hi> Durham.</p>
            <p>Ariſtophanis Comaediae Duae, Plutus &amp; Nubes, cum Scholiis Graecis Antiquis. Qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus adjiciuntur Noctae quaedam, ſimul cum Gemino Indice. In uſum ſtudioſae Juventutis.</p>
            <p>The Reaſons of Praying for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> In a Sermon preach'd before the Queen at <hi>White-Hall,</hi> on the <hi>Faſt-Day,</hi> being <hi>Wedneſday, Auguſt</hi> 29. 1694. By <hi>Thomas Comber, D. D. Dean of</hi> Durham, and Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain in Ordinary to their Majeſties. <hi>Printed by their Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Daily Office for the Sick; Compil'd out of the holy Scriptures, and the Liturgy of our Church; with occaſional Prayers, Meditations and Directions.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59696:59"/>
            <p> The Catechiſms of the Church, with Proofs from the New Teſtament, and ſome additional Queſtions and Anſwers, divided into twelve Sections, by <hi>Z. I.</hi> D. D. Author of the Book lately publiſh'd, Entituled a Daily Office for the Sick, with Directions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Church-Catechiſm, with a brief and eaſie Explanation thereof, for the Help of the meaneſt Capacities and weakeſt Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, in order to the eſtabliſhing them in the Religion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> By <hi>T. C.</hi> Dean of <hi>Durham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Pantheon,</hi> repreſenting the Fabulous Hiſtories of the <hi>Heathen</hi> Gods, and moſt Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Heroes: In a ſhort, plain, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar Method, by the way of Dialogue, for the Uſe of Schools. Written by <hi>Fra. Pomey,</hi> of the Society of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> Author of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Dictionary, for the Uſe of the <hi>Dauphin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Bedae Venerabilis opera quaedam Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gica, nunc primùm edita, neonon Hiſtorica antea ſemel edita. Acceſſerunt Egberti Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiepiſcopi Eboracenſis Dialogus de Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticâ Inſtitutione, &amp; Aldhelmi Epiſcopi Scireburnenſis Liber de Virginitate, ex codi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceantiquiſſimo emendatus.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:59696:60"/>
            <p> Diſquiſitio in Hypotheſin <hi>Baxterianam</hi> de Foedere Gratiae, ab Initio &amp; deinceps, ſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per &amp; ubiqueomnibus indulto, &amp; adhuc a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Ethnicos &amp; extra-evangelicos vigente ac valente ad ſalutem. Autore Carolo Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bothamo, Eccleſiae Anglicanae Presbytero Norfolcienſi, <hi>S. Th. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Q. Horatii Flacci Opera: Interpretatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne &amp; Notis illuſtravit <hi>Ludovicus Deſprez.</hi> Cardinalitius Socius ac Rhetor Emeritus, Juſſu Chriſtianiſſimi Regis, in uſum Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſſimi Delphini, ac Sereniſſimorum Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipum Burgundiae, Andium, Biturigum. Huic Editioni acceſſere Vita Horatii, cum <hi>Dacerii</hi> Notis ejuſdem Chronologia Horatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, &amp; Praefatio de <hi>Satira Romana,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>L. Annaei Flori</hi> rerum Romanarum Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome; Interpretatione &amp; Notis illuſtravit Anna Tanaquilla Fabri Tilia, Juſſu Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſſimi Regis in uſum <hi>Sereniſſimi Delphini.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Compendium <hi>Graecum</hi> Novi Teſtamenti, continens ex 7959. Verſiculis totius N. Teſtamenti tantum Verſiculos 1900. (non tamen integros) in quibus omnes univerſi Novi Teſt. Voces una cum Verſione La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina inveniuntur: Auctore <hi>Johanne Luſden.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59696:60"/>Philoſ. Doctore, &amp; Linguae Sanctae in Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demia Ultrajectina Profeſſore Ordinario. Editio Quinta.</p>
            <p>A Second Admonition to the diſſenting Inhabitants of the Dioceſs of <hi>Londonderry,</hi> concerning Mr. <hi>Boyſe</hi>'s Vindication of his Remarks on a Diſcourſe concerning the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of Men in the Worſhip of God, with an Appendix containing an Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Boyſe</hi>'s Objections againſt the Sign of the Croſs. By <hi>William</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Derry.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>The End of the Catalogue.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
